<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Meeting on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/meeting/</link><description>Recent content in Meeting on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/meeting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting 2017: HeJus Achievements and Plan</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/csm_group_photo_2017_web_cbdc94603d.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting 2017: HeJus Achievements and Plan" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Same time of year, different Helmholtz center!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year, in February, the Helmholtz Juniors annual meeting took place in the beautiful Heidelberg, where the old city and the state-of-the-art cancer research facilities of the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.dkfz.de/en/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;German Cancer Research Center&lt;/a&gt; (DKFZ) meet! Thirty-four representatives from all Helmholtz centers joined the 3-days meeting. We were fortunate that the spokespersons of &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.phdnet.mpg.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Max Planck PhDnet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.leibniz-gemeinschaft.de/en/careers/the-next-generation-of-researchers/leibniz-phd-network/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Leibniz PhD Network&lt;/a&gt; joined us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0699_2-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0699_2-300x200_hu_891bd2c3c90917e3.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0699_2-300x200_hu_536b6c00eecd6db.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="A session by DKFZ graduate program director Dr. Lindsay Murrells"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DKFZ was very hospitable. During the meeting, the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.dkfz.de/en/phd-program/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;graduate program&lt;/a&gt; director, Dr. Lindsay Murrells, introduced the research at DKFZ and its graduate school to us. On the DKFZ campus, there are 3,000 personnel working on cancer research, 540 of which are doctoral researchers. She also introduced us to the various services that the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.dkfz.de/en/career-service/Careers.html?m=1487783040" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;career center&lt;/a&gt; provides for both doctoral researchers and &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.dkfz.de/en/postdoc-program/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Postdocs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0861-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0861-300x200_hu_83447e8c6447bf0f.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0861-300x200_hu_cb1e19ca1061984.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="HeJus dinner in the old town of Heidelberg"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a very special tour in two of the most modern facilities for cancer research and treatment in Europe, the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.dkfz.de/en/medphysrad/workinggroups/ultrahighfieldmr/ultrahighfieldmr.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;High-Field Whole Body MR (7 Tesla)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.klinikum.uni-heidelberg.de/index.php?id=112189&amp;amp;L=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Heidelberg Ion Beam Therapy Facility (HIT)&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the arrangements of DKFZ HeJus, Danja and Elias, we also enjoyed our time in the old town of Heidelberg. Photo credits go to Elias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What we achieved in 2016:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the meeting, &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2017/02/meet-dagmara-and-elias-our-spokespersons/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Dagmara&lt;/a&gt;, HeJus Spokesperson in 2015/16, pointed out that one of the HeJus&amp;rsquo; goal is to improve doctoral researchers&amp;rsquo; working conditions, yet the occasion to hear them out are limited to the survey and the NextGen conference. She said, &amp;ldquo;If we cannot hear from them, we cannot help them.&amp;rdquo; What we achieved and plan to achieve clearly reflect this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HeJus are organized into 4 working groups: &lt;strong&gt;working conditions, survey, communications, and events&lt;/strong&gt;. On the first day, the speakers of each group reported on what their groups have accomplished in 2016. No surprise there, the achievements were astonishing! The events group reported on &lt;a class="link" href="https://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2016/11/nextgen-2016-conference/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;NextGen 2016&lt;/a&gt;, the first German-wide meeting of Helmholtz doctoral researchers. We also met members of the dedicated team of talented PhD students at GEOMAR, Kiel organizing NextGen. The group also gave us a glimpse of then preliminary &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/press_and_media/events/nextgenhelmholtz_2017/program/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;program&lt;/a&gt; of NextGen@Helmholtz 2017 in Kiel&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The working conditions group has worked with all HeJus for years on the most optimal &lt;strong&gt;working conditions statement&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;65% TVöD E13 payment, 30 days of vacation, and a contract of minimum 3 years from the beginning with the doctoral project as the main job objective.&amp;rdquo; The working conditions group sent their statement to &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/ueber_uns/die_gemeinschaft/praesident/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Dr. Otmar D. Wiestler&lt;/a&gt;, the President of the Helmholtz Association. Prof. Wiestler kindly offered his time to respond to the statement (we will publish his response in a following blog post). All HeJus has sent the statement to their respective directors, and Lisa, the HeJu from GEOMAR, has shared with us a remarkable success story. GEOMAR Dokteam has met with the Director, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.geomar.de/en/mitarbeiter/d/pherzig/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Peter Herzig&lt;/a&gt;, concerning the statement, and within 1 month &lt;strong&gt;GEOMAR changed the status of 13 in-house and Max Planck stipend holders into 75% TVöD contracts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the largest research association in Germany, and believing that science is not isolated from the political and societal scenes, the working conditions group also prepared a &lt;strong&gt;questionnaire and sent it to the main German political parties&lt;/strong&gt; about their views on scientific research. The HeJus are awaiting for the answers which will be publicly available to guide the German voters prior to the elections in September, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The efforts of HeJus spokespersons in 2015/16 Dagmara and Elias have secured the HeJus &lt;strong&gt;a budget of 50,000 EUR per year for 3 years&lt;/strong&gt;. The spokespersons are the contact point and external representation of the HeJus. They communicate regularly with other PhD networks and with the Helmholtz Association. We now have a direct contact at the headquarters to &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talent/funding_programs/doctoral_students/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Dr. Johannes Freudenreich&lt;/a&gt;, who is known for his efforts promoting of young and early researchers with focus on postdocs, supervisors training and the newly formed international research schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The survey group shared with us the news that they have finished preparing &lt;strong&gt;the 2017 survey&lt;/strong&gt;. The available budged allowed them to run the survey on a secure platform. The survey covered many issues that are integral to the doctoral researchers such as: funding, supervision, graduate schools, working conditions, career plans, and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, all the updates, news, events and outreach have been brought to you by the communications group! We communicate the HeJus news to you through our various channels: the &lt;strong&gt;blog,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/company-beta/17993833/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; . We report on the various events that HeJus take part in. We also outreach for new HeJu members and introduce HeJus working groups to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What we will achieve in 2017:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0790-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0790-300x200_hu_4b895ff1004f2985.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0790-300x200_hu_b690af559c540beb.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Speakers of HeJus, Max Planck PhDnet and Leibniz PhD Network"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second day, we went on preparing our plan for 2017. The highlights are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs/status/839768720243322880" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Network of Networks (N^2):&lt;/a&gt; The HeJus, Max Planck PhDnet and Leibniz PhD Network have been in close contact and exchange of experiences since the beginning of each of them. Now they formed N^2, a network for all doctoral researchers at all non-university research organizations in Germany. The first participation of N^2 was at the &lt;a class="link" href="https://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2017/05/march-for-science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;March For Science&lt;/a&gt;. N^2 plans joint events and call for interested doctoral researchers to participate in it. Stay tuned to know more about N^2 formation and activities here on the blog soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NextGen@Helmholtz at GEOMAR: NextGen is very special because it is an exclusive event of Helmholtz Association doctoral researchers. It has a unique nature as a multidisciplinary meeting. Its program includes a certificate-based science communication training. The alumni session is meant to provide the now students with various ideas of what is after-PhD. Through NextGen, we know about facilities at other Helmholtz Centers for perhaps future collaborations. Because of that all, the Hejus communicated to the graduate schools at all the centers to provide financial support and credit points for their doctoral researchers registering for NextGen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0901-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0901-300x200_hu_20034a4764a21166.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/06/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2017-hejus-achievements-and-plan/images/DSC0901-300x200_hu_e7545dbb16b97869.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="From right: the newly elected speakers Konstantin and Giulia, and treasuress Lara of the HeJus"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With their enthusiasm and expertise, we elected Giulia and Konstantin as the HeJus spokespersons for the year 2017. Giulia Caglio [&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.mdc-berlin.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine&lt;/a&gt; (MDC), Berlin] has been a member of the HeJus communications group. You certainly read her blog posts &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/about-the-authors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In the DokTeam, Giulia was proactive and had a sense of responsibility to improve the working conditions at her institute. She plans to pursue the same as a spokesperson of the HeJus. Konstantin Kuhne [&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Zentrum Dresden-Rossendorf&lt;/a&gt; (HZDR), Dresden] was the HeJus treasurer for the past year. He gained an overview on the organization within the Helmholtz Association. We will hear from them here on the blog, and from the newly elected treasuress Lara Grünig from the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.hzg.de/index.php.de" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht Centre for Materials and Coastal Research&lt;/a&gt; (HZG).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what does that meeting mean for &amp;ldquo;non-HeJus&amp;rdquo;? We have a few recommendations in that regard!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now officially in all HeJus documentations and communications we are all called &lt;strong&gt;“Doctoral Researchers”&lt;/strong&gt;! A term that precisely describes our day-to-day job at the largest research association in Germany, and empowers us to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctoral researchers are 50% of the working force at the Helmholtz Association and a significant fraction of the scientific output and publications is produced by doctoral researchers. The working conditions and survey groups &lt;strong&gt;need your input&lt;/strong&gt; from all the centers and to react upon it to improve the contracts and working conditions of the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for a series of &lt;strong&gt;interviews and interesting research project from all the Helmholtz centers&lt;/strong&gt; here on the blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask the HeJu representatives of your center and your graduate school for our &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why to become a HeJu?&amp;rdquo; flyer&lt;/strong&gt;. Consider becoming the HeJu representative of your center in the next elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get involved!&lt;/strong&gt; If you missed NextGen 2017 registration, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;like us&lt;/a&gt; and be ready for N^2 events and NextGen 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/images/LOGO_Blue2.png" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On July 13, the Helmholtz Juniors (you may know as HeJus) conducted their meeting in Berlin, which lasted for two days. More than 30 Juniors came from Helmholtz Centers all over Germany to join the Midterm Meeting taking place at the Helmholtz Association’s Headquarters (HGF) in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For weeks before the meeting, the Juniors were preparing the agenda and gathering information across all centers and the HeJus working groups on the working conditions of PhD students and also the major problems that the students at each center are facing. The agenda of the Midterm Meeting included discussions on the PhD contract model that HeJus Working Conditions group has been working on, and a session by &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.southampton.ac.uk/oes/postgraduate/research_students/km1g14.page" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Kyle Mayers&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Southampton on the British doctoral system. The agenda also included the ongoing preparations for the soon coming Helmholtz PhD conference “&lt;a class="link" href="https://indico.scc.kit.edu/indico/event/229/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;NextGen@Helmholtz&lt;/a&gt;” taking place this September at HZI in Braunschweig. The HeJus met up with the new members joining this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank you for following our live updates via &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and for your comments. Stay tuned for more details on the meeting&amp;rsquo;s recommendations!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Mid-Term Meeting 2015 in Berlin</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med2.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Mid-Term Meeting 2015 in Berlin" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th and 21st of July, the Helmholtz Juniors Mid-Term Meeting took place at the Helmholtz Association&amp;rsquo;s Head Office (HGF) in Berlin. It was the second Mid-Term Meeting ever and proved to be a great opportunity to meet each other again, to discuss the latest progress and problems, and to improve the cooperation of the Helmholtz Juniors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the first day of the meeting, we were welcomed by Caroline Krüger from the Helmholtz head office. The working phase was opened up with presentations from all Helmholtz Juniors working groups on the activities of the last half year and on future plans for the upcoming half year. Afterwards two guests from the Helmholtz Head Office gave a parallel session on two of the main topics we deal with. Elsbeth Lesner was guest of a discussion round on working conditions, PhD contracts and stipends. Jennifer Schevardo gave a firm presentation on different networks within the Helmholtz Community with a focus on the new “Helmholtz &amp;amp; Friends” Alumni network. “Helmholtz &amp;amp; Friends” aims to strengthen the Helmholtz-Feeling within the Association and initiates the build-up of a new network of peers that provide exchange of knowledge basically concentrating on social skills and leadership (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/helmholtz_friends/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz &amp;amp; Friends&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med-300x200_hu_ba9d877df27e559e.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med-300x200_hu_73c72265f989b0b5.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Helmholtz Juniors at the Helmholtz Association’s Head Office in Berlin"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch – a delicious one by the way – our next guest was Sabine Helling-Moegen, the administrative head of the German Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases (DZNE). She gave a brief overview of the history of the German “Großforschungseinrichtungen” and of the the Helmholtz Association and described the process from narrow research topics towards nowadays program oriented research and the program oriented funding (“Programmorientierte Förderung”, POF). The interesting talk and the following discussion gave us the opportunity to gain a better understanding of mechanisms and politics in science and education in general and in the Helmholtz Association, in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last part of the first day was dedicated to a discussion on an overall strategy of the Helmholtz Juniors and on tasks for upcoming half year and their priority:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focus for the working conditions group: reduce number of in-house stipends and increase number of vacation days to 28 or 30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve the motivation of all PhD students to be part in the local PhD representative initiatives and in the Helmholtz Juniors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enhance visibility of the Helmholtz Juniors: Only if we are visible, we can change something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strengthen the connection to the HGF head office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strengthen our network to other groups which work for improving working conditions in science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve continuity after handover to new Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day was concluded with dinner in a nice restaurant in Berlin‘s center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4515_med-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4515_med-300x200_hu_c1c8fb1f4d714433.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4515_med-300x200_hu_8ce64420117126d4.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Discussing the Helmholtz Junior’s future plans"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day of our Mid-term meeting was dedicated towards group work. The working conditions group recapitulated their meeting with Elsbeth Lesner from the previous day. The Event group started planning a Helmholtz PhD day which should take place in 2016. Both, the Survey and the Communications working groups attended an Q&amp;amp;A session with Jan-Martin Wiarda, Bianca Berlin and Janine Tychsen from the Helmholtz Communications and Media Relations Office. The three of them were faced with several questions on internal and external communication issues. Besides receiving useful answers, possible contacts for our communication-related issues, and insight into the current projects of their group, we were encouraged to raise a critical voice inside and outside of the Helmholtz Association whenever necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a wrap-up and a basket of tasks for the upcoming months, we finished our Mid-term meeting in the early afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we, the Helmholtz Juniors, want to thank all our guests, the Helmholtz Association&amp;rsquo;s Head Office and the events working group. The meeting was a great success and will motivate us and enhance our future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Goodbye 2014, Hello 2015: Bring it on!</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/goodbye-2014-hello-2015-bring-it-on/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/goodbye-2014-hello-2015-bring-it-on/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/goodbye-2014-hello-2015-bring-it-on/images/HeJu2015.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Goodbye 2014, Hello 2015: Bring it on!" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The New Year 2015 is already a couple of days old. Let’s have a look back on the work of &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="Helmholtz-Juniors"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Juniors&lt;/a&gt; (HeJu) in 2014 and take a look ahead to what’s to expect for 2015. Yuan (see authors) compiled our current &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/wp-content/uploads/sites/15/2015/01/HeJu-Newsletter2014.pdf" title="HeJu-Newsletter 2014 (pdf)"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HeJu-Newsletter2014&lt;/a&gt; which gives you an overview about the work of 2014 and our contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From January 22 to 24, 2014 the HeJus were kindly hosted by the Helmholtz Centre Dresden-Rossendorf (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=0" title="HZDR"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZDR&lt;/a&gt;) in Dresden for their annual meeting. During that meeting the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" title="working groups"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;working groups&lt;/a&gt; presented their achievements of the previous term, and new goals where set for the next HeJu, namely us (most members are only active for one year, a list of currently active members you can find &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/current_helmholtz_juniors/" title="HeJu members"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The most important goals being set the realization of the Helmholtz PhD survey 2014 (survey group), the active participation in the formulation of an updated version of the official Helmholtz &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Doktoranden/Leitlinien_Doktorandenausbildung.pdf" title="PhD guidelines"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;doctoral training guidelines&lt;/a&gt; (working conditions group), the finalization of “the PhD booklet” (communication group) and coming up with a new concept for an interdisciplinary event for PhDs of the Helmholtz Association (HA) (events group). We also spoke with a Helmholtz official about financial support for our plans and the function and position of the HeJu within the HA. Additionally, we welcomed a representative of &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.phdnet.mpg.de" title="PhDnet"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;PhDnet&lt;/a&gt;, the PhD network of the Max Planck Society (MPG). Although being an official part of the MPG, they are known to be very critical towards their mother organization and fight for just working conditions and appropriate remuneration. They shared valuable information about their experience within the MPG and how they are organizing themselves. Vice versa Sripriya, one of our spokespersons last year, attended the annual meeting of PhDnet in Heidelberg later in 2014 and brought back interesting ideas for funding new events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also discussed current problems. For instance only 14 of the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/helmholtz_centres_networks/helmholtz_centres/" title="Helmholtz centres"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;18 Helmholtz centres&lt;/a&gt; were represented at the HeJu annual meeting, despite the centres agreeing to cover travel expenses for the meeting. Some representatives complained that the general will of students to engage for a representative function (meaning the DokTeams or PhD initiatives) at the individual centres was rather low among PhD students. It was also pointed out that there were difficulties in reaching all the PhD students working at one centre due to size, structural organization and the lack of networking possibilities. Other problems included the identification of the basic needs of PhD students of different subjects and at different centres (for instance: significantly lower salaries for PhDs in life science than for PhDs in engineering or similar subjects, not to mention PhDs in social science or the ones living on stipends).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From July 21 to 22 the HeJu met again at a mid-term meeting at the HA’s headquarters in Berlin thanks to the efforts of the events team who managed to get us comfortable in Berlin, and in touch with the headquarters for 2 days. This time 16 out of 18 centres were represented. A more detailed report about this event you can find &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/" title="HeJu Mid-Term Meeting 2014"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This gave us the possibility to check up on the progress of single projects and to rethink others. Just before the meeting the survey group put their questionnaire online and was able to show first figures (I hope you all took part!). The fully analysed results will soon follow (see below). Also a new working group was formed: the embodiment group. Inspired by the organization of PhDnet, its members were to evaluate if becoming an official body of the HA (including a fixed annual budget) was worth giving up our current independence. The working conditions group was actually able to leave their critical mark on the new doctoral training guidelines (to be released this year) and the communication group was invited to take a look behind the HA public relation department in order to increase HeJu&amp;rsquo;s visibility at the Helmholtz centres and beyond. As a result, we have this blog online since September 2014 and we hope you enjoy reading it. We will use it to keep you all updated about our work and also hope to get some discussions going about PhD life (or &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2014/11/life-after-phd/" title="Life after PhD"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;after life&lt;/a&gt;) in general. Feel free to leave your comments and ideas and have a look on our &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="Helmholtz-Juniors"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and our new &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors" title="HeJu Facebook"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;facebook page&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what’s to come in 2015? Big milestone ahead of course: the annual HeJu meeting at the Alfred Wegener Institute (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.awi.de" title="AWI"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;AWI&lt;/a&gt;) in Bremerhaven this week from January 14 to 16! There we will see how happy YOU are and at which centre you are happiest according to the results of the Helmholtz PhD survey. Information, each individual centre is also very interested in. We will present an online version of the PhD booklet (due to difficulties with the layout, a print version will only be available at a later time point but, we wanted to make sure that you can access this information asap). We hope that many of new and old PhD students in Germany will find it very useful. We will discuss our impact on the new Helmholtz doctoral training guidelines and the pros and cons of an official embodiment within the HA. We will see what concept the event group came up with and if we will again get support for an additional mid-term meeting. One of the more difficult topics is the question if PhD students should get stipends or contracts. There is a will of the HA to provide each PhD student with a contract rather than a stipend but, this is, of course, not yet reality. Given the tight financial situation for personnel money in science in general and at certain centres in particular, this will still be an issue in the future. An issue that probably has to be discussed with Otmar Wiestler, now head of the German Cancer Research Centre (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.dkfz.de" title="DKFZ"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;DKFZ&lt;/a&gt;), who will replace Jürgen Mlynek after 10 years as HA&amp;rsquo;s new president in September this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very important point will be the handing over of our work to the ones of you that will take over our tasks. Due to the short HeJu terms, a thorough transfer of information is crucial for an efficient continuation. Thus, let’s look forward to what the next HeJu generation will have in store for us. I will surely keep checking up on the news here. Good luck! :)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/MeetingProfM.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the end of July the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="HeJus"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Juniors&lt;/a&gt; (or more informally “HeJu”) got together for their mid-term meeting at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/" title="Helmholtz Association"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Association&lt;/a&gt;’s head office in Berlin. It was the second time we met this year after our first meeting at the Helmholtz Center Dresden-Rossendorf (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=139" title="HZDR"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZDR&lt;/a&gt;) in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is useful to mention here that the HeJu’s are not an official body of the Helmholtz Association, but a diverse group of volunteering PhD students who are committed to improve PhD working conditions and connect PhDs within the Helmholtz Association as well as within Germany (look at this &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/helmholtz_centres_networks/helmholtz_centres/" title="Helmholtz Centers"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; to see where we are located). This includes a cacophony of emails, phone calls, doodle lists, literature research and skype conferences. And all that we are trying to manage on the side to our own demanding PhD projects, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_318452cf8586dd02.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_5c0d26a0a1eaf992.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Members of the communication group are discussing content and style of the new HeJu Blog. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I was really looking forward to the meeting as we had set ambitious goals back in January and our predecessors had informed us that it might be difficult to keep up the motivation for our projects throughout the entire year. Thus, we decided to get together again already after half a year to renew our HeJu energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there we were: One and a half days full of reports, heated discussions, brainstorming and coffee overflow. First of all our spokespersons Nicholas and Sripriya and our four &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" title="Working Groups"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;working groups&lt;/a&gt; presented the progress so far. The main achievements have been the active participation in an update of the Helmholtz Association’s official PhD guidelines (which virtually has some effect on all Helmholtz PhD students), the finishing of our “Helmholtz PhD booklet” (we will keep you posted about this!) and the launch of this year’s &lt;a class="link" href="http://heju-survey.de" title="HeJu Survey"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;PhD survey&lt;/a&gt; (where every PhD student under Helmholtz can actually help to improve the conditions, hopefully you all took part. But, don’t worry if not, it’s still possible until Sep 19th!!! Go for it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_bc838b8887356475.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_a10fb63526318854.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Our events group organized the mid-term meeting and currently develops concepts for future PhD events. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our “events” group who was busy organizing this meeting we’ve been in close contact with officials of the Helmholtz Association and the direct feedback was helping a lot to shape common goals and to identify certain (im)possibilities. For instance, what financial support can we expect and what are the advantages and disadvantages of becoming an official body of the Helmholtz Association? A topic so fundamental, that the formation of a new working group was required to evaluate its pros and cons. But, a special treat for us was the visit of Prof. Dr. Jürgen Mlynek, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/president/" title="HA president"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;president&lt;/a&gt; of the Helmholtz Association, who took some time to welcome us personally in the headquarter and also stayed for a quick Q&amp;amp;A session (see header). How much closer can you get as a PhD student to the very head of your research organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_abed3c62ea1a0cea.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_b731d6a0c9399ad.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The newly established embodiment group will evaluate how to position the HeJu’s within the Helmholtz Association in the future. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During several sessions the individual working groups discussed and developed new ideas and eventually set the goals for the rest of the term. Furthermore, we were lucky to talk with the public relations officials, who gave us vital support on our visibility and communication structure as well as an insight into their day-to-day work. A result of which we have this brand new Blog you happened to be reading right now and the new &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors?fref=ts" title="HeJu FB"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HeJu’s logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is left to do for this year? Of course, the discussion on the PhD guidelines is not over yet and will go on. One goal, for example, is to increase contract positions for PhDs in relation to scholarships. The “survey” group will have a busy time analyzing the survey results and wrapping that up until January next year, when the HeJu’s meet again at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.awi.de/en/home/" title="AWI"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Alfred Wegener Institute&lt;/a&gt; in Bremerhaven. The PhD booklet will be published and available for everyone who’s interested (some interviews with the people involved will be up as well). We are also planning a special event where PhD students can connect and get information on career options and this Blog will be filled with more articles about our work as HeJu’s and topics about PhD life in general. Feel free to comment and ask questions below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715.jpg"
width="1000"
height="715"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_ba63b2c24e57ba16.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_62e4c2da3df96f65.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="As you might already have figured out, all that talking and discussing made our heads dizzy. We tried to counteract that feeling over a few drinks at Berlin’s open air summer nightlife locations. During which we discussed if the competition for Germany’s sexiest scientist award would be an appropriate HeJu-event to organize. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="139"
data-flex-basis="335px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>