<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Heju-Mental-Health-Awareness-Month on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/heju-mental-health-awareness-month/</link><description>Recent content in Heju-Mental-Health-Awareness-Month on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/heju-mental-health-awareness-month/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to communicate your problems</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/03/how-to-communicate-your-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/03/how-to-communicate-your-problems/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/03/how-to-communicate-your-problems/images/Blog-banner.png" alt="Featured image of post How to communicate your problems" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Author: Anonymous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open communication is key for a good working environment, effective collaboration, and a healthy relationship with your co-workers and supervisors. The ability to communicate well is crucial for working efficiently and successfully- especially during a doctorate. It is well known that a doctorate comes with a multitude of challenges unrelated to the actual research itself. Young researchers often face problems that are not only related to completely neutral working topics but are also on a personal level, which brings emotions into the mix. This includes problems with co-workers and quite often with the supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being emotionally involved makes it more challenging to communicate issues effectively and in a constructive manner. The real problem then is often not the actual problem, but rather the stimulated emotions. To make matters worse, communicating feelings at work is still sometimes perceived as unprofessional, weak, and inappropriate when precisely the opposite is true. Good communication is essential for maintaining not only a healthy working environment, but also good mental health and a free mind. In addition, learning how to communicate effectively leads to both personal and interpersonal growth. So, &lt;strong&gt;what IS the best way to communicate your problems and how it makes you feel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is no one single solution for all problems, here are some general pointers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before reacting impulsively with strong emotions, take a deep breath and try to distance yourself from the situation. Practice some self-awareness. What is it that you are feeling? Understand your own emotions, so you can express yourself more clearly. Depending on the situation, it might be helpful to talk to a trusted friend or colleague about the circumstances. Maybe write down what the problem is and how it makes you feel. Where did this problem originate, and do you have a solution you could propose? Do you think you can solve the problem by yourself? If not, don’t hesitate to tackle the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When addressing problems, remember: the time and place matter. Choose a moment when both parties are receptive. Talk somewhere where you will not be interrupted or disturbed. Both parties should take the time needed to discuss with no time limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When communicating your problems, try to be as clear and specific as possible. Explain your problems and interests and if possible, give concrete examples. This helps the other party understand the issue and makes the issue tangible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People tend to quickly feel attacked, therefore when talking about the problem, use “I-statements”. Employ phrases such as “This gives me the feeling&amp;hellip;” or “This gives me the impression&amp;hellip;” and avoid direct confrontations like “You are&amp;hellip;” or “You always do XYZ&amp;hellip;”. Criticism in any situation should remain constructive. By staying with your emotions, it shifts the focus to your feelings and promotes empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to express how a problem is affecting &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, how it makes &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; feel. This more constructive than blaming or attacking the other person directly, which should be avoided. Direct criticism of a person can hurt the other party, incite retaliation, and create even more problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different points of view for every problem. The main goal is for all parties to understand each others’ points of view. This can help deescalate the situation and hopefully lead to a resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to the other party and allow them to answer without interruption. Keep in mind that their feelings are also valid. Try to understand their point of view and listen to their interests. If the situation becomes emotional, make sure to stay calm and respectful to foster a more positive outcome. Be open to apologizing when needed or appropriate. Maybe the other party did react out of emotions as well and both of you can approach each other. Try to stay in the present with a focus on the future. Do not be too hung up on the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are often dependencies in a working environment which you cannot easily dissolve or also do not intend to. That is why it is important to seek for a solution together which is suitable for all parties. Try to find areas of agreement upon which you can build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use expressions such as: “I feel like we are stuck, and I understand that the underlying reasons could be this and this. I would need a more supportive collaboration, and therefore I would appreciate X and Y. Of course, I want to support you on the same level. What would you need? How can we improve the situation?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After communicating your problem, take some time and reflect on the situation and on what was discussed. Keep up the communication to ensure progress in resolving the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel that the communication barrier is too high, involving a mediator can be a good idea. This can be a supervisor, but also an ombudsperson. Companies and institutes do often have persons specially trained in helping handle and resolve such situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in some working environments, communicating your problems as a female comes with even more challenges such as being perceived as weak, and when speaking up, pushy. Here, it is important to not let yourself be silenced. If you face unjust criticism, stay consistent, stay strong. Such reactions say more about them and their inability to interface with strong women and less about you. In such situations it might be helpful to speak up and clearly reject such statements. Do not tolerate sexism at any point. Females communicating problems in a constructive, calm manner should not be subject to being called “tough” and “pushy” and being told to get out of their “victim-hood”. This is a failure in communication by the other party, and we suggest asking for a mediator or talking to a supervisor. Do not, however, let it stop you from communicating your problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, communication styles differ from culture to culture. While Germans tend to have a very direct way of communication, this is different in other cultures. The German way of communication can be perceived as impolite or offensive. However, in some cultures, silence is a strong form of communication, which can be missed if one is unaware of such culture-specific cues. These cultural differences should always be kept in mind and considered, especially in our very international work environment.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your voice, your advocacy tool</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2024/04/your-voice-your-advocacy-tool/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2024/04/your-voice-your-advocacy-tool/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2024/04/your-voice-your-advocacy-tool/images/Copy-of-Survey-2024-version-2-Blogbanner-2.png" alt="Featured image of post Your voice, your advocacy tool" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;written by Aga Seretny, Speaker Survey 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To all our dedicated doctoral researchers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, the Helmholtz Juniors, understand that our shared passion for science and research is accompanied by unique challenges, such as increased work load, mental stress, and potentially even power abuse. This survey serves as your platform to voice concerns and experiences related to supervision quality, power dynamics, and mental health status within your centers. By sharing your story, you are advocating for a healthier, more supportive academic environment for both yourself and your peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information as catalyst for change&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your insights are invaluable in helping us to be at the forefront of championing positive changes within the academic system, no matter how gradual the progress may seem. The information you share with us through this survey serves as a beacon, guiding the improvement of doctoral programs worldwide. Your participation brings to light the realities of doctoral research, enabling stakeholders to address issues proactively. It&amp;rsquo;s through understanding your experiences that we can identify areas for improvement and advocate for a healthier academic ecosystem. This is your opportunity to be part of a transformative movement, leveraging information to carve out a better path for all doctoral researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking out for yourself and future doctoral researchers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking part, you are not just sharing your own experiences but also paving the way for a more supportive environment for those who follow. Our reports help visualize that many of the challenges you face are shared across the entire academic community of doctoral researchers, reinforcing the fact that you are not alone in your journey. This collective insight highlights common issues, underscoring the importance of a unified approach to advocacy and improvement. Together, we can build a legacy of resilience, support, and success, ensuring that the challenges of today become the lessons and victories of tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why we do the survey every 2 years?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistency is key to understanding and initiating lasting change. Conducting this survey biennially allows us to track progress, identify new challenges, and adapt strategies to meet the evolving needs of doctoral researchers. This regular pulse-check ensures that our efforts are not just reactive but proactive, keeping the well-being of doctoral researchers at the forefront of academic development. We are aware that change within academia can be slow, but by continually gathering your feedback, we aim to be steadfast advocates for positive evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Navigating challenges together&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overcoming the delays and intricacies of German bureaucracy, particularly doing it side-by-side while pursuing doctorates, posed a significant challenge for us. The path to delivering this survey was fraught with hurdles that, at times, seemed insurmountable due to the complex nature of administrative processes we faced. However, the unwavering dedication and teamwork of key supporters within our community turned these potential roadblocks into milestones, ensuring your voices could be effectively heard. This journey underscored the power of unity and resilience, demonstrating that no obstacle is too daunting when we come together with a shared goal. Thank you to everyone who contributed, making this survey a reality and championing the cause of doctoral researchers across the Helmholtz Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you for your participation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your time, honesty, and courage in participating in this survey are immensely appreciated. Every response adds a vital piece to the puzzle, bringing us closer to an academic environment that cherishes and nurtures the mental health and well-being of its researchers. Thank you for lending your voice to this crucial cause. Together, we are stronger, and together, we can make a difference. Your input today is a step towards a more inclusive and nurturing academic tomorrow – take the survey now!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Combating the stigma of mental health in academia</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2023/05/combating-the-stigma-of-mental-health-in-academia/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2023/05/combating-the-stigma-of-mental-health-in-academia/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2023/05/combating-the-stigma-of-mental-health-in-academia/images/Mental-health-awareness-month-1230-%C3%97-400px-5.png" alt="Featured image of post Combating the stigma of mental health in academia" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Written by Hugo Enrique Reyes Aldana&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us are familiar with the famous Roman saying “Mens sana in corpore sano”, which could be translated into “a healthy mind in a healthy body”, and almost sure there is a translation in your native language in case Latin nor English is one of them. This reflects the fact that even in ancient times the health of the mind was as important as the health of the body. But at some point, that shifted. Mental problems became something to be hidden or neglected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why mental health was long disregarded in discussions of health is the stigma attached to mental illness. The stigmatization of mental illness has been pervasive and long-standing in many cultures, often leading to individuals suffering in silence and not seeking help. Unfortunately, this is particularly true in academia, where the pressure to succeed, the competition for funding and positions, and the constant need to publish can all take a toll on one&amp;rsquo;s mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academia is known for its culture of perfectionism, where mental toughness is often equated with success. This mindset can lead individuals to ignore their mental health needs and feel ashamed or weak for experiencing mental health challenges by fearing judgment or discrimination from their colleagues and peers if they talk about their mental health struggles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stigma can have severe consequences, such as deterring individuals from seeking help, delaying diagnosis and treatment, and ultimately harming their overall health. To combat it, it is crucial to normalize discussions around mental health and acknowledge that challenges related to it are common and natural in academia. Seeking help is a sign of strength, not weakness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Universities and academic institutions should prioritize resources and offer support for their students and staff. Mental health support should be easily accessible, affordable, and destigmatized. Additionally, research institutions should promote mental health awareness and provide education around to reduce the stigmatization of it and broaden its understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also crucial to encourage open communication and support between colleagues and peers. Academic institutions should promote a culture of support and encourage individuals to share their mental health struggles with others, as sometimes building connections and empathize could help to ease the struggles. This can help reduce feelings of isolation and create a sense of community among those struggling with mental health challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic institutions should also recognize and acknowledge the impact of academic stress and pressure on mental health. High-pressure academic environments can exacerbate existing mental health conditions or even create new ones. Therefore, it is essential to create a supportive and nurturing environment that prioritizes mental health and well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For these and other reasons it that we as HeJus would like to contribute to this ongoing discussion and generate awareness during this month. Along it, we will be sharing content related to Mental Health that you will be able to find in the survey and well as our social media channels. So, remember to take care of yourself and your fellow doctoral researchers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mental Health Awareness - Part 2: Supervision</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/banner2.png" alt="Featured image of post Mental Health Awareness - Part 2: Supervision" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Health Awareness&lt;/strong&gt; is a concern all year long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in some countries May is the Mental Health Awareness Month, in other its October. We want to use both!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For May we have something different prepared. The &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.universitaetsverlagwebler.de/_files/ugd/7bac3c_6974dfc41c054e3b94ff8590718fe819.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Mental Health Paper&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a class="link" href="https://de.linkedin.com/in/ivona-kafedjiska-227166ba?trk=public_post_share-update_actor-text&amp;amp;original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.linkedin.com%2F" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Ivona Kafedjiska&lt;/a&gt;, Lea Heckmann, Vanessa Pires, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pankhuri-s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Pankhuri Saxena&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Jana Lasser made quite an impression amongst the community this year [1]. Our post summarizes the most important parts of each subtopic included in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2nd part of the series: &lt;strong&gt;Supervision&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/1-1-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/1-1-759x569_hu_4fe51751592337f0.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/1-1-759x569_hu_8b80da402d681637.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/2-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/2-759x569_hu_3fe210054822de5b.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/2-759x569_hu_509a4894afc0006d.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/3-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/3-759x569_hu_d04fb75bb16ebf44.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/3-759x569_hu_20b633819bb867ce.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/4-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/4-759x569_hu_5b4bc895dfa020d4.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/4-759x569_hu_f0c2b5d05d111047.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/5-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/5-759x569_hu_9bd0a2f638a9c864.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/5-759x569_hu_4b1199cb73272b23.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/6-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/6-759x569_hu_25176948ff27a074.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/6-759x569_hu_cb790eb283b77829.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/7-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/7-759x569_hu_277135e264e5df84.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/7-759x569_hu_33c812472db13d5e.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/8-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/8-759x569_hu_1490a5881a467db0.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/8-759x569_hu_9224edc5e65b2a3c.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/9-759x569.png"
width="759"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/9-759x569_hu_809745fb0a7042bf.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/06/mental-health-awareness-part-2-supervision/images/9-759x569_hu_156bf8209dc19ea3.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]    Kafedjiska, I., Heckmann, L., Pires, V., Saxena, P., &amp;amp; Lasser, J. (2022). The Mental Health Crisis among Doctoral Researchers – Findings and Best Practices. &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift für Beratung und Studium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt;(1), 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images: Jakob Rauscher, Aniket Raje&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mental Health Awareness - Part 1: Workload</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/Slide1.png" alt="Featured image of post Mental Health Awareness - Part 1: Workload" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Health Awareness&lt;/strong&gt; is a concern all year long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in some countries May is the Mental Health Awareness Month, in other its October. We want to use both!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For May we have something different prepared. The &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.universitaetsverlagwebler.de/_files/ugd/7bac3c_6974dfc41c054e3b94ff8590718fe819.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Mental Health Paper&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a class="link" href="https://de.linkedin.com/in/ivona-kafedjiska-227166ba?trk=public_post_share-update_actor-text&amp;amp;original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.linkedin.com%2F" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Ivona Kafedjiska&lt;/a&gt;, Lea Heckmann, Vanessa Pires, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pankhuri-s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Pankhuri Saxena&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Jana Lasser made quite an impression amongst the community this year [1]. Our post summarizes the most important parts of each subtopic included in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1st part of the series: &lt;strong&gt;Workload&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/1-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/1-1000x1000_hu_653ac4e8948fec9e.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/1-1000x1000_hu_82b37b52f8af9b9e.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/2-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/2-1000x1000_hu_cda462b6e5bac00d.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/2-1000x1000_hu_d9dafed1ca6ce7f5.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/3-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/3-1000x1000_hu_f631a006fcbeb16a.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/3-1000x1000_hu_276b0325405f3dfc.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/4-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/4-1000x1000_hu_b62ca7b8467792d1.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/4-1000x1000_hu_d7d7a8389414fc54.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/5-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/5-1000x1000_hu_eb4e566ab2be71b5.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/5-1000x1000_hu_e84e9013db42d530.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/6-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/6-1000x1000_hu_704d11fa2282bd52.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/6-1000x1000_hu_eafc2606d503a8ff.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/7-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/7-1000x1000_hu_99404a57d515c340.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/7-1000x1000_hu_dc4fb770c4417bf8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/8-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/8-1000x1000_hu_7a988cce45722d55.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/8-1000x1000_hu_379b1a1b2b8c528a.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]    Kafedjiska, I., Heckmann, L., Pires, V., Saxena, P., &amp;amp; Lasser, J. (2022). The Mental Health Crisis among Doctoral Researchers – Findings and Best Practices. &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift für Beratung und Studium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt;(1), 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images: Jakob Rauscher, Aniket Raje&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) - Welcome</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-welcome/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-welcome/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-welcome/images/Welcome-banner_blog.jpg" alt="Featured image of post HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) - Welcome" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take a moment, sit back, breathe and relax.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know that doing a PhD can be really challenging, not only scientifically but also on the personal side. There have been enough studies talking about “we need to pay attention to our students&amp;rsquo; mental health” [1], and that’s good. Mental health is a topic that is often overlooked or even dismissed. Very often we have to deal with the feeling of constant failure, impostor syndrome, heavy expectations and it is just overwhelming. Also, the requirements for a good PhD such as learning a lot of new things and dealing with many complex and large projects combined with stressful situations in the lab and private life can sometimes make it hard to cope. Add to that the whole process of moving to another country, as around 40% of is Doctoral Researchers in the Helmholtz Association have [2] – leaving friends and family behind. And that can be an additional burden to carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are not alone!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s face it: you have probably experienced at least one of these real bad moments during your PhD. So, the first thing we want to make sure you know is that you are not alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially during these crazy recent times of a worldwide pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us not ignore the importance of staying healthy in both mind and body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Health Awareness Month&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Helmholtz Juniors wants to invite you to join us this October for our Mental Health Awareness month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our post series (in parallel, same email series were sent to all Helmholtz Docs on every Thursday) bundles a lot of information and good practices to keep your minds healthy. Furthermore, we discuss the current state of Doctoral Researchers‘ mental health in Germany and around the world. We provide information on how to identify possible stressors and signs of stress in your life as well as some potential tips on how to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for our mental health awareness posts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy this reading as it will be a great opportunity for a precious 5 min break from work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helmholtz Juniors: the PhD network working to improve our situation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wondering about the origin of this campaign? Let us introduce ourselves: we are the Helmholtz Juniors, the PhD network of the Helmholtz Association. We represent around 8000 Doctoral Researchers to the head office and the public, and our efforts focus on assessing and improving our situation during the PhD. You might have heard of some measurable results from our work, such as the general increase of salaries and implementation of contracts instead of stipends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us together destigmatize mental health and do the first step together: &lt;strong&gt;Let’s talk about it!&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also remember, help can be right there, with a very long and deep breath and a simple and easy chit chat with a fellow Doctoral Researcher who might have been there already and can share some experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And finally: you survived 100% of your worst days so far. Congratulations on that! So take a moment, sit back, breathe and relax. You deserve it.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Information that we want to share:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Jena is hosting a Mental Health Webinar Series starting next Monday with a 7 interesting topics!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to check their programm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.uni-jena.de/forschung/exzellenzstrategie/jena&amp;#43;alliance&amp;#43;life&amp;#43;in&amp;#43;focus/mental&amp;#43;health&amp;#43;day&amp;#43;2020&amp;#43;webinar&amp;#43;series" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.uni-jena.de/forschung/exzellenzstrategie/jena+alliance+life+in+focus/mental+health+day+2020+webinar+series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03489-" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03489-&lt;/a&gt;1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Brain health</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-brain-health/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-brain-health/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-brain-health/images/brain-health.jpg" alt="Featured image of post HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Brain health" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often talk about heart and lung health, etc. but we seldom talk about brain health which is undeniably central to all our health. The brain is like any other organ. During our Mental Health Awareness month we actually talk a lot about stress. Stress is often portrayed as having only relatively short lasting psychological impacts, but it also alters the biochemistry happening in your body and especially your brain and therefore actually having also long lasting physiological impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you properly take care of it, you will reap the most fulfilling benefits. As the renounced neuroscientist Dr Daniel Amen said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“When your brain works right, you work right and when your brain is troubled your life is troubled”&lt;/strong&gt; [10].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, then the question is how someone can improve ones brain health?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are the most important practices, according to a various number of studies, for an ultimately better brain health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-brain-health/images/brain-health.jpg"
width="957"
height="957"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-brain-health/images/brain-health_hu_d8a04aa12784b44e.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-brain-health/images/brain-health_hu_a591b7bfe79cd595.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep &amp;amp; Relaxation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good sleep is the backbone of all brain health [16]. Without good sleep, your brain cannot function. Memory loss, for instance, is often associated with a lack of sleep. When you are sleeping, a structure in the brain called the hippocampus recalls and consolidates recent memories - and without sleep, this natural process is halted [4]. Furthermore, during sleep, the brain gets rid of waste products such as beta-amyloid, which if aggregated to plaques is associated with Alzheimer’s disease [7]. Sleep also improves mood and the immune system and may lead to weight loss [5,6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://healthybrains.org/pillar-nutrition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Food &amp;amp; Nutrition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cells all over your body need to produce ATP – aka the “energy molecule”. During this process, the cells release free radicals. Excess free radicals can lead to oxidative stress and damage of cells - including nerve cells (oxidative stress) [8]. The main factor that increases or decreases the number of free radicals in your blood is food. Healthy food, especially vegetables, which are full of antioxidants like broccoli and spinach, decrease free radicals [13]. Unhealthy food normally contain high amounts of sugars and carbohydrates which can increase the number of free radicals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healthy food can also improve the necessary chemistry of the brain leading to better cognition. For example, healthy fats like Omega 3 have been shown to improve memory while also being beneficial for the whole body [9].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://healthybrains.org/pillar-physical/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Physical Exercise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercising 20 min a day doing any kind of aerobic activity has shown to have great benefits [12]. It makes the cells of your body much stronger and less prone to oxidative stress. It also improves blood flow to the brain and hence more oxygen and nutrients delivered to the nerve cells. Exercise also stimulates chemical changes in the brain that enhance learning, mood and thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies show that practising meditation regularly has great benefits. It helps not only managing stressful situations but also improves memory. In one study it is shown that meditation changes the structure of the brain [2]. It increases the volume of the hippocampus which is responsible for learning and memory and decreases the volume of the amygdala which is responsible for fear and anxiety. If this got you interested and you want to get started with meditation, take a look at these two books [11,15].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://healthybrains.org/pillar-social/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Social Interaction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a shocking study, a group from Harvard medical school reported that feelings of loneliness may have detrimental consequences on cognition, e.g memory loss [3]. Being engaged in social activity is an important pillar of your brain health. Try at least to stay in touch with your family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we would like to recommend these two books [10,17], which are full of tips and good practices that boost your brain health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://healthybrains.org/pillars/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://healthybrains.org/pillars/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hölzel, B. K., Carmody, J., Vangel, M., Congleton, C., Yerramsetti, S. M., Gard, T., &amp;amp; Lazar, S. W. (2011). Mindfulness practice leads to increases in regional brain grey matter density. Psychiatry research: neuroimaging, 191(1), 36-43.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Donovan, N. J., Okereke, O. I., Vannini, P., Amariglio, R. E., Rentz, D. M., Marshall, G. A., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Sperling, R. A. (2016). Association of higher cortical amyloid burden with loneliness in cognitively normal older adults. JAMA Psychiatry, 73(12), 1230-1237.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walker, M. P., &amp;amp; Stickgold, R. (2006). Sleep, memory, and plasticity. Annu. Rev. Psychol., 57, 139-166.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Besedovsky, L., Lange, T., &amp;amp; Born, J. (2012). Sleep and immune function. Pflügers Archiv-European Journal of Physiology, 463(1), 121-137.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beccuti, G., &amp;amp; Pannain, S. (2011). Sleep and obesity. Current opinion in clinical nutrition and metabolic care, 14(4),402.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shokri-Kojori, E., Wang, G. J., Wiers, C. E., Demiral, S. B., Guo, M., Kim, S. W., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Miller, G. (2018). β-Amyloid accumulation in the human brain after one night of sleep deprivation. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 115(17), 4483-4488&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lobo, V., Patil, A., Phatak, A., &amp;amp; Chandra, N. (2010). Free radicals, antioxidants and functional foods: Impact on human health. Pharmacognosy Reviews, 4(8), 118.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amen, D. G., Harris, W. S., Kidd, P. M., Meysami, S., &amp;amp; Raji, C. A. (2017). Quantitative erythrocyte omega-3 EPA plus DHA levels are related to higher regional cerebral blood flow on brain SPECT. Journal of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease, 58(4), 1189-1199&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Books&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="10"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The End of Mental Illness by Daniel Amen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A New Earth: Awakening to Your Life&amp;rsquo;s Purpose, by Eckhart Tolle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spark: The Revolutionary New Science of Exercise and the Brain, by John J. Ratey, Eric Hagerman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genius Foods: Become Smarter, Happier, and More Productive While Protecting Your Brain for Life, by Max Lugavere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Brain&amp;rsquo;s Way of Healing: Remarkable Discoveries and Recoveries from the Frontiers of Neuroplasticity by Norman Doidge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardwiring Happiness: The New Brain Science of Contentment, Calm, and Confidence by Rick Hanson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why We Sleep: Unlocking the Power of Sleep and Dreams by Matthew Walker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Genius Life: Heal Your Mind, Strengthen Your Body, and Become Extraordinary by Max Lugavere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Exposing the problem</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health.png" alt="Featured image of post HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Exposing the problem" /&gt;&lt;h3 id="mental-health--why-do-we-care"&gt;Mental Health – Why do we care?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mental health of Doctoral Researchers has been increasingly analysed during the last years, often with alarming results. Major concerns regarding the well-being of early career researchers are depression, anxiety, harassment and a difficult work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do studies say?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Graduate Assembly (2014) reported that 47% of Doctoral Researchers of the University of California, Berkeley met the threshold for depression. A recent study by Levecque et al. (2017) analysed the situation of more than 3000 Doctoral Researchers in Belgium and found that the risk for psychiatric disorders in academia is higher than in other highly-educated groups. 32% of Doctoral Researchers are at risk of a common psychiatric disorder, such as depression. Main reasons were work-family interfaces, job demands and job control, and the leadership style of the supervisor (Levecque et al., 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Nature study, 29% of 5700 Doctoral Researchers listed mental health as an area of concern, with half of them getting help for depression or anxiety caused by their PhD study (Woolston, 2017). A follow-up Nature study in 2019 showed that things seem to get worse; 36% of 6300 PhDs from all around the globe seeking help for depression and anxiety related to their PhD project. Also, one-fifth reported bullying, while another fifth experienced discrimination or harassment (Nature, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EPFL Doctoral III survey (2019) draws a similar image, 20.7% of the 1043 participating Doctoral Researchers experienced &lt;strong&gt;bullying&lt;/strong&gt; or behaviours that may constitute as bullying, which includes aggressive behaviour, being undermined and being isolated and ignored by people at work. Symptoms of depression were associated with experienced bullying behaviour. If there is evidence of bullying more than 90% of respondents showed depressive symptoms (EPFL, 2019). Another reason for the critical mental health situation is that success is measured in publications, citations, funding and impact. The autonomy of research is reduced or removed when funding, publications and impact are part of the universities formal monitoring and evaluation system, and when supervisors judge the failure or success of Doctoral Researchers (Nature, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did we find?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/power-abuse.png"
width="357"
height="624"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/power-abuse_hu_372919eba0264d67.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/power-abuse_hu_8f41315090e3c21f.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="57"
data-flex-basis="137px"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health.png"
width="482"
height="624"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health_hu_1c4a440b0244b746.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health_hu_88639f2007bcde78.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="77"
data-flex-basis="185px"
&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 2019 Helmholtz Juniors survey, we tried to get an overview of the mental health of all Doctoral Researchers within the Helmholtz Association. The survey used a shortened STAI questionnaire. The high number of working hours - 66 % work more than 41h while even 18 % work more than 50 h a week - and high conflict potential - 16 % reported conflicts with superiors are critical influences on the mental health of young Doctoral Researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the questionnaire indicated 22 % showed signs of moderate to severe depression and 70 % showed signs of moderate to high state anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are, sadly, similar to the findings of the already presented studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the first step on finding solutions and ways to tackle a problem is knowing about it in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We´re working on various strategies, as Helmholtz Juniors on our own, as well as in joined projects with individual centres and of course with the Helmholtz Association’s Headquarters in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And we would like to hear your opinion on that topic!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think are the biggest challenges for keeping a good mental Healh while doing your PhD or in science in general?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you encountered a hostile workplace atmosphere?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want to help us create a more sustainable work environment in academic research?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We would love to hear your thoughts and ideas!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – How to be happy?</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/How-to-be-Happy.png"
width="1441"
height="360"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/How-to-be-Happy_hu_62a3c4e0721c4eae.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/How-to-be-Happy_hu_4dc4f46a95b0d0d4.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="400"
data-flex-basis="960px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to be happy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;„If only we’d stop trying to be happy we’d have a pretty good time.“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edith Wharton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic is quite a controversial and also philosophical one. Let´s be honest here: we can´t guide you to fundamental happiness. There´s no neat trick that works for everyone. If so it would be a more peaceful and relaxed world. What we want to do is make you &lt;strong&gt;think&lt;/strong&gt;. Because even if you´re totally against everything we will write down here: thinking about it may bring you a step further to your version of happiness. &lt;strong&gt;So join us on this ride!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While being happy might be the ultimate goal and achievement of everyone’s life, achieving true happiness is not that simple. The term &lt;em&gt;Happiness&lt;/em&gt; can be divided into basically two varieties. The first is a short term, nearly ecstatic rush of Happiness. This Happiness-rush is quite a cruel creature – once you were able to capture a glimpse of it, it is gone already again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So would it be recommended at all, to chase the illusion of a life that consists only out of happy moments?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;„Gotta have a little sadness once in a while so you know when the good times come.“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bob Ross&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second variety is the long term, innerly peacefull and lasting happiness. And that is the variety of happiness that is more sustainable. While the ecstatic happiness rushes are what spice up life, the fundamental happiness is the one that makes you feel satisfied. The one that let´s you feel relaxed, being balanced and in peace with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life can be exhausting, boring and full of dickhe… ahem, people that are hard to get along with. But life can also be full of joy, fun and full of nice and great people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are the one that defines your very own life.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, this is a hell of a task. Most likely the most important and hardest task you ever signed yourself up for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are three questions you can ask yourself to align your course to destination &lt;em&gt;Happiness&lt;/em&gt;, and they might help you to get this task done in the best way possible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you working for?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Might it be solely to be able to pursue a luxury lifestyle, three times extravagant holidays a year, a sports car that goes from 0 to 100 in a blink of an eye? Or might it to be able to provide a good life for your family. Or doing your part in changing the world with your very own everyday science – hopefully to the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those aims are extremely diverse and your very own. They will also change often in life – but being aware for what YOU are working so hard for whatever it might be will help you to keep being motivated. And you then also know, what you really WANT to spend your money on. And please, don´t feel sad because you feel like the lifestyle you pursued 10 years ago was wasteful – it was the lifestyle you wanted to live and that brought you (hopefully) joy those days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you passionate about?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being passionate about what you´re doing is one of the most crucial things when it comes down to joyfulness and in the greater scheme happiness. If you´re passionate about what you´re doing, then work goes easy and you actually like to work and furthermore – it doesn´t feel like work. But it´s not obligatory to be passionate about your work. If you´re passionate about beer, coffee or deliciousness in general – be passionate! If you´re passionate about motorsports, skiing or any other sport – be passionate! If you´re passionate about video games and/or eSports – be passionate! If you´re passionate about arts, painting, sculpting or craftsmanship - be passionate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially Hobbies are there to bring joy – and not meant to generate any income. Although this doesn´t exclude each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passion is the spark that lit the fire in your heart for a specific topic – and also keeps it burning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do I chase Happiness?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this sounds controversial: happiness is, most of the time, only short-lasting – those rushes we talked about earlier. Happiness is what you feel when you had a good experiment, got compliments, won some poster prize or won a game of Monopoly. Chasing this kind of happiness means, only wins, only great results and only external love from other people will count – and they´re hard to get. And if those don´t happen, you´re starting to feel unhappy until you get a glimpse of it again. You can´t really chase happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key, in our opinion, is to chase joy. You can feel joyful for doing a good job for yourself. You can feel joyful while playing the game – although you might not win it. You can feel joyful in appreciation that you were invited to speak to a broad audience that are all experts in their fields. And you will feel joyful by doing something you´re passionate about. You will feel joyful treating yourself with something from your bucket or wish list. You might feel joyful if you enjoy a beautiful sunset with a beautiful cup of coffee in your hands. Go and enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go and chase joy instead of happiness. Because that way, fundamental happiness will be your most loyal companion.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is also the last one of our Mental Health Awareness Month post series. We honestly hope it lit a spark of thought on this important topic. And that you and your mental health benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember: You Are Not Alone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for all that loyal companions that read through all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/Heju-cat-1-189x300.jpg"
width="189"
height="300"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/Heju-cat-1-189x300_hu_d934b2f4627b2454.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/Heju-cat-1-189x300_hu_18fb11307743c2bf.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="63"
data-flex-basis="151px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/Heju-cat-2.jpg-300x224.png"
width="300"
height="224"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/Heju-cat-2.jpg-300x224_hu_9fab2556ff9cb1f2.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-how-to-be-happy/images/Heju-cat-2.jpg-300x224_hu_51444cdc3e211e2c.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="credit: HeJu communication group"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="321px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#HeJuCat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you still feel a bit down, here´s something that should cheer you up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/rZcmIMypGkg?t=9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://youtu.be/rZcmIMypGkg?t=9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Possible Stressors and Signs of Stress</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors.png" alt="Featured image of post HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Possible Stressors and Signs of Stress" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stressors can be various, but for Doctoral Researchers, it mostly starts with a high workload and high expectations – which potentially activates a downwards spiral: This can lead to less time for hobbies (friends, sports etc.), which can be leading to sleeplessness and therefore tiredness and in the end potentially social isolation. But everyone deals with stress differently. Some seem pretty robust when it comes to stress – mainly because they´ve learned how to personally deal with stress. While some seem very prone to stress and react with severe psychological as well as physiological symptoms. In the end, nobody is immune to stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you been waking up in the middle of the night because you were thinking about a project you need to finish soon? Do you feel overrun because you can´t keep up with the project outline? Do you feel chased by deadline after deadline? Are you feeling tired a lot? Do you have twitching muscles, like your eyelids or fingers? Has your appetite changed? Have you gained or lost a lot of weight? Have you felt struggled to concentrate on work? If you answered yes to any of these questions, then you are probably stressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors.png"
width="907"
height="906"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors_hu_5c727616c1815ccc.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors_hu_c25a5ead9faa8f3f.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People tend to overlook these early signs or do not take them seriously. We think, in a few days everything will be fine again. We think we need to function or otherwise we´re worthless. We think our whole future depends on this one talk we have to hold within the institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But often these signs last - and you slowly start getting used to them. But the stress itself &lt;strong&gt;is still there&lt;/strong&gt; and the signs of stress get worse. At some point, they might even lead to the burnout syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it is very useful to learn for yourself which signs of stress you are experiencing. Knowing your personal symptoms already helps to prevent further stress and prevent letting it slip and get worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, by increasing your knowledge in this topic you might be able to identify such signs in your colleagues who might be eager to have someone understand what they are going through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is no sign of weakness to admit that you are stressed and need a break!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, be honest with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A non-stressed you is way more productive than a completely stressed-out you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep that in mind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>