<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Interviews on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/interviews/</link><description>Recent content in Interviews on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/interviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Check out the interview (4/5) here! Our HeJu survey team discusses about mental health for doctoral researchers in our academic system</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/12/check-out-the-interview-4/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-discusses-about-mental-health-for-doctoral-researchers-in-our-academic-system/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/12/check-out-the-interview-4/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-discusses-about-mental-health-for-doctoral-researchers-in-our-academic-system/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/12/check-out-the-interview-4/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-discusses-about-mental-health-for-doctoral-researchers-in-our-academic-system/images/interview-4.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (4/5) here! Our HeJu survey team discusses about mental health for doctoral researchers in our academic system" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anxiety? Depression? Feeling upset/worried/tense? Maybe you have experienced (one of) these during your PhD, but have you ever thought these are all warning signs for your mental health? Or in another words, why should we care and how?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our newest survey (report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  ), we have (as always) put these points into perspective and asked our DRs about status of their mental health . Below, our survey team will discuss some of the important aspects about mental health for PhDs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gPhSh9rTXgg"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Check out the interview (3/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is power abuse and how to deal with conflict</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/12/check-out-the-interview-3/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-power-abuse-and-how-to-deal-with-conflict/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/12/check-out-the-interview-3/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-power-abuse-and-how-to-deal-with-conflict/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/12/check-out-the-interview-3/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-power-abuse-and-how-to-deal-with-conflict/images/malle-and-micha.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (3/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is power abuse and how to deal with conflict" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is power abuse in the academic system? Is it a something new, or why it is gaining more and more attention?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our newest survey (report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  ), we have (as always) put these points into perspective and asked our DRs about power abuse and conflicts. Below, our survey team will tell you some of the key results from the survey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QV6UaGdGzVk"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/images/interview-2.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weather you are currently thinking of doing a PhD or you are already a doctoral  researcher (DR), it might always quite interesting to know how is it like to be a doctoral researcher at the largest scientific organization in Germany. More specifically, how are DRs networked? How diverse are DRs? or to be of most interest of many of you, how well is a DR being paid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our newest survey (report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  ), we have (as always) put these points into perspective and asked our DRs what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center. Below, our survey team will tell you some of the key results from the survey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sY_L269sST4"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Check out the interview (1/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you the motivation and execution of our 2019 HeJu survey</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-1/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-the-motivation-and-execution-of-our-2019-heju-survey/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-1/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-the-motivation-and-execution-of-our-2019-heju-survey/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-1/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-the-motivation-and-execution-of-our-2019-heju-survey/images/Picture1.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (1/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you the motivation and execution of our 2019 HeJu survey" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being a doctoral researcher (DR) can sometimes lead us to a &amp;ldquo;solitary&amp;rdquo; journey. For instance, even within the same discipline, the researches we do still need certain extent of novelty so that many of us might never find some one doing exactly the same thing and have an in-depth chat about our passions. On the other hand, being doctoral researchers can also bring us a solidary benefit. We are that many (even within the Helmholtz society, there are currently about 8,500 DRs) and the greater challenges (beyond our specific research topic) are so similar for all of us (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03459-7%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03459-7)&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, staying connected with our peer DRs through networks as well as showing the representative status quo of our DR community is crucial to improve our living/working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is an example we have done as Helmholtz Juniors (HeJu) for showing our representative status quo of our DRs. We conduct a Helmholtz-wide PhD survey every two years and publish the results. We also communicate with the administrative units at each center by our local HeJu representatives and try to promote the living/working conditions for our DRs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our newest survey report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And below is the interview with our survey team to explain you our motivation and execution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CqtTU_E4z40"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Meet Bernhard and Danja, of our survey group</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/07/meet-bernhard-and-danja-of-our-survey-group/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/07/meet-bernhard-and-danja-of-our-survey-group/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/07/meet-bernhard-and-danja-of-our-survey-group/images/LOGO_Blue2.png" alt="Featured image of post Meet Bernhard and Danja, of our survey group" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;To follow up our interview series, this month we would like to introduce you to the former and the current speakers of the Survey group, Danja and Bernhard. Danja worked on the establishment of the survey 2017, arranging the technical aspects since January 2016. Bernhard, the speaker of the 2017 survey group, had the task to run the survey and will lead the survey team through the analysis phase. Ultimately, the results of the survey will be made public and will be useful to get a coherent image of the status of the doctoral researchers among the Helmholtz Centers and to focus on the next steps we would like to take to improve our situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Survey is of great importance for Helmholtz Juniors. Survey 2014 was the ground on which we based our request to have better and comparable contracts among the centers. You will read about this in a soon-coming blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, we would like to leave the word to Danja Sarink, from &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.dkfz.de/en/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Deutsches Krebsforschungszentrum&lt;/a&gt; (DKFZ) and Bernhard Schuck from &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.gfz-potsdam.de/startseite/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;GeoForschungsZentrum&lt;/a&gt; (GFZ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="question-first-could-you-tell-us-a-bit-about-your-phd-project"&gt;Question: First, could you tell us a bit about your PhD project?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Danja: I’m doing my PhD in cancer epidemiology, using a large European cohort study to analyze the relation between the Receptor Activator of Nuclear Factor κβ-axis and breast cancer. My aims are mostly explorative: if and how these biomarkers relate to breast cancer in humans, but they could potentially be used to improve e.g. risk prediction or primary prevention of breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bernhard: Being a structural geologist, I focus on the Alpine Fault in New Zealand, which is the plate boundary between the Pacific and the Australian Plate. I aim to better understand what the rocks can tell us about the deformation mechanisms associated with large earthquakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-we-are-all-part-of-the-helmholtz-association-what-do-you-think-is-the-value-of-being-part-of-it"&gt;Q: We are all part of the Helmholtz association. What do you think is the value of being part of it?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: I think the network it creates. It gave me the opportunity to meet other doctoral researchers from different fields, as well as to get a broader idea of research and academia in Germany outside my institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: I agree with Danja. In addition, collaboration between individual centers representing a broad variety of research fields encourages us to think out of the box and to try new attempts to tackle scientific tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-how-have-you-first-learned-about-helmholtz-juniors-and-why-did-you-decide-to-join"&gt;Q: How have you first learned about Helmholtz Juniors and why did you decide to join?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: I learned about HeJu when I joined one of the working groups of the PhD council at the DKFZ. What drew me to HeJu was the more overarching nature of and the fact that it aims to address bigger picture things, that can be difficult to address on your own or even within your institute. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-you-are-part-of-the-survey-group-that-is-vital-to-the-heju-to-gather-information-and-decide-future-strategies-how-would-you-define-the-work-done-by-your-group-and-what-could-be-achieved-with-it"&gt;Q: You are part of the survey group, that is vital to the HeJu to gather information and decide future strategies. How would you define the work done by your group and what could be achieved with it?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: We work in a two year cycle; one group sets up and runs the survey, the next analyses the data and publishes results. We worked closely with Helmholtz headquarters on e.g. legal aspects of the survey. Most of our work is in the background, but over the last few months our main task was communication; we did our best to annoy all HeJus into advertising the survey at their centers, and Immo Korte at Helmholtz Headquarters has been great in helping us reach all the Helmholtz centers. As for future strategies, I think ‘gather information and decide future strategies’ captures the aims of the survey group well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: The survey and its results are the essential base for any discussion between the HeJus and any institution within the Helmholtz Association. However, this important role required that the workflows within the group had to be professionalized. This is one of the greatest achievements of past year’s survey group under Danja’s leadership. Data handling and security follow the essential guidelines and templates are prepared so that the next group can minimize the effort to be invested in formal requirements and focus on the aspects they want to get out of the survey. A major achievement of the survey is that it is widely accepted as reference to set minimum standards for the working conditions of doctoral researchers at the individual centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-being-a-member-of-the-survey-group-is-a-great-responsibility-and-probably-requires-a-good-amount-of-your-time-why-did-you-decide-to-join-this-group"&gt;Q: Being a member of the survey group is a great responsibility and probably requires a good amount of your time. Why did you decide to join this group?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: It actually seemed like less work than the working conditions or events group! I knew I wanted to join either the communications or survey group and decided for the survey group because I get to use some of my epi/public health skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: In my case the decision was quite trivial. Benedikt, at that time the second HeJu from my center, was already part of the working conditions group. I don’t think communication is my strongest skill and the events group had already a fair number of members, I decided to join the smallest group: the survey group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-what-are-the-biggest-challenges-you-are-facing-or-faced-working-in-your-group"&gt;Q: What are the biggest challenges you are facing or faced working in your group?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;B: Besides the need to meet all the formal requirements, one of the biggest challenges is to keep the group member’s motivation high. Running and evaluating the survey is a quite time-consuming task and the potential for frustration is high. Bearing in mind that all group members are volunteering the speaker has to ensure that group sticks to the schedule and still has some fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D: I have to agree with Bernhard here that group-work can be fun and horribly frustrating at the same time, but I think we’ve also had a great core group of people in the survey group in both 2016 and 2017. For me, dealing with data protection and security issues was a learning curve. I knew it existed of course but I had never been directly involved with or responsible for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-what-do-you-think-is-the-next-challenge-of-the-survey-group-or-the-heju-in-general"&gt;Q: What do you think is the next challenge of the survey group or the HeJu in general?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: for the survey group, analyzing the data from this survey. We are also, for the first time, trying our hand at a time series analysis of some specific topics to see if there are any changes over time. For HeJu, a lot of work has been going on around working conditions and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/press_and_media/events/nextgenhelmholtz_2017/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;NextGen@Helmholtz&lt;/a&gt;, which I think is absolutely awesome! While running the survey (and also in setting up NextGen@Helmholtz I think) we noticed that not nearly all docs know what HeJu is or does. We exist to represent all docs, so I think this is a challenge to tackle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: Whereas analyzing the data of the survey 2017 and to carry out the time series analysis are goals to be achieved in the next months, having a proper hand-over to the next survey group will be the final challenge for this group. It would be a fantastic turnout on the time invested by last year’s group members, if we manage to provide the next survey group with all the information necessary to focus on preparing the questionnaire, setting-up and running the next survey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-recently-a-lot-of-awareness-rose-on-the-correctness-of-data-communication-and-on-science-in-general-culminating-in-the-march-for-science-what-is-your-opinion-on-such-manifestations-and-movements"&gt;Q: Recently, a lot of awareness rose on the correctness of data communication and on Science in general, culminating in the March for Science. What is your opinion on such manifestations and movements?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: The awareness and very public discussion on science is great. On the short term it’s relevant to scientists, but I think that in the long term it’s relevant to everyone that good unbiased science exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: My personal point of view is that these events are essential to communicate to society what science is about. A profound methodological base accepted by the scientific community is essential to achieve meaningful results. However, what these results tell us, how they should be interpreted and what consequences should arise, should and often is open to debate. There is no single expert to explain how the world works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-in-your-opinion-what-is-the-major-challenge-scientists-are-facing-in-their-relationship-with-society"&gt;Q: In your opinion, what is the major challenge scientists are facing in their relationship with society?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;B: Society invests tremendous amounts of money in science. Especially within the Helmholtz Association this money is often used to conduct fundamental research under fantastic working conditions. Scientists have to acknowledge that society has a right to get informed about their research in a way everyone is able to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D: I agree with Bernhard, he also makes a very good point in saying “…in a way everyone is able to understand”. Scientists are good at disseminating work to other scientists, but communication to the general public mostly happens through media. It would be great to see more focus on science communication in a broader form than manuscripts, conferences, and press releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-coming-to-a-conclusion-we-would-like-to-know-what-you-would-like-to-say-to-someone-interested-in-joining-the-helmholtz-juniors-should-they"&gt;Q: Coming to a conclusion, we would like to know what you would like to say to someone interested in joining the Helmholtz Juniors. Should they?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: Definitely! There is work involved of course but, if you’re interested, it’s also rewarding and the different working groups give you the chance to develop very different skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: Absolutely. As doctoral researchers our training is closely related to the research we conduct, be it in the lab or when it comes to presenting the results in conferences and papers. Joining the HeJus encourages you to develop a number of soft skills like time and conflict management but also to see what and how things are done in different disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="q-as-a-last-question-would-you-like-to-share-your-favourite-moment-in-the-heju-and-explain-why-it-was-important-for-you"&gt;Q: As a last question, would you like to share your favourite moment in the HeJu and explain why it was important for you?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;D: I think HeJu has had a few fantastic achievements over the last year, with our letter about working conditions to the Helmholtz board and BMBF (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bmbf.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung&lt;/a&gt;) and our first NextGen@Helmholtz conference. I will have to go a bit smaller though; my highlight was running the survey. We invested a lot of time and had to jump some unexpected hurdles on the way, so it was very satisfying to see the live result!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B: The first NextGen@Helmholtz at HZI (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz-hzi.de/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Zentrum für Infektionsforschung&lt;/a&gt;) last year in Braunschweig with doctoral researchers from all over the country coming together and presenting what they do was a fantastic experience. But I agree with Danja, running the survey was my favorite moment, too. We spent so much time during the last year on all the preparation and had a rough time trying to finish the survey this February. Seeing that the survey was finally running and that the number of participants was constantly increasing was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Meet Dagmara and Elias, our spokespersons</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/02/meet-dagmara-and-elias-our-spokespersons/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/02/meet-dagmara-and-elias-our-spokespersons/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/02/meet-dagmara-and-elias-our-spokespersons/images/DSC_7670_web.gif" alt="Featured image of post Meet Dagmara and Elias, our spokespersons" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today we would like to open a new series of interviews on the Helmholtz Juniors blog, where you can get to know the members of the HeJus, what are their responsibilities and what are they passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with our spokespersons, Elias and Dagmara, that represent us officially outside the HeJus, coordinate all the different groups inside the HeJus and motivate us all the time. Elias comes from DKFZ in Heidelberg, Dagmara from GEOMAR in Kiel and they are spokespersons since February 2016, when they were elected during the annual meeting of the Helmholtz Junior. They were asked some questions about their work, duty and ideas about doctoral researchers and HeJus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you will enjoy the reading as we did the writing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interview was edited for brevity and clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="question-would-you-like-to-briefly-tell-us-what-are-you-working-on-in-your-graduate-research"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question: Would you like to briefly tell us what are you working on in your graduate research?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dagmara:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; As a doctoral researcher I work at GEOMAR, the Helmholtz Centre for Ocean Research in Kiel. My research is focused on trace metal chemistry in seawater. Trace metals are biologically vital micronutrients to all marine organisms. The ultimate aim of my project is to quantify fluxes of these essential nutrients from the coastal waters to the open ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elias:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I’m interested on molecules that are regulating the intrinsic properties of blood stem cells. For me, they are quite an interesting bunch. They are full of regeneration and differentiation potential, but they are mostly sitting around doing nothing, only working when they are really forced to do so. However, those principally “lazy” stem cells are capable of replenishing a whole organ, the blood system, when they are called for their job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-when-have-you-decided-to-join-the-hejus-and-how-you-got-to-know-the-association"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: When have you decided to join the HeJus and how you got to know the association?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I became a PhD representative at GEOMAR and through that, I was informed about HeJu activities; it sounded very interesting and I decided to join the Helmholtz Juniors in February after the election to institutional PhD representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; It’s quite a straightforward story: both at the University Heidelberg and within my Helmholtz Center, the German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ) I was already engaged in the representation of doctoral researchers, and by this I also got to know previous HeJu members and the network itself. I was quite curious about the interdisciplinarity of the group and the direct exchange between researchers from different fields of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-you-were-elected-spokesperson-how-is-it"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: You were elected spokesperson, how is it?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Being a spokesperson is a lot of responsibility and at times a lot of work along with my PhD project. However, I enjoy working with a vast group of highly motivated and enthusiastic people across so many disciplines. There are so many different points of views and approaches and it’s a great opportunity to learn from others. It has been a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Fascinating, absolutely! To some people, the position might seem to involve only a lot of tedious discussions and email-writing, without any visible progress. Sometimes that is in part true, but hey! in every “job” there are those days. I’ve really learned so much during this year about communication, science management and, in fact, quite a bit about myself. I think especially by attending big official meetings and by being forced to think more about larger structures and programs rather than specific little problems, one gets a better idea what this sometimes overused “big picture” phrase actually means. Seeing so many bright people working jointly to move something forward and getting all the loose ends of little projects together: it is just very rewarding in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-which-responsibilities-do-you-have-and-how-your-work-inside-the-hejus-changed"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Which responsibilities do you have and how your work inside the HeJus changed?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; My work didn’t change as I became a spokesperson as soon as I became HeJu ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Together with my co-speaker, Dagmara, we’re trying to coordinate all the different topics within Helmholtz Juniors and to enable everyone to achieve our goals efficiently – in the end, everyone at HeJus is a volunteer, and thus we’re also mainly making sure to get rid of obstacles on their way. A big part of this year was spent strengthening the bonds with other research associations. Also, as the face of the HeJu towards the public, we’re the first contact point to journalists and political parties. Apart from that additional duties, my efforts in the working condition group has not changed: I’m still very active in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-do-you-think-the-work-of-hejus-can-contribute-to-ameliorate-the-doctoral-researchers-conditions-inside-helmholtz-institutes"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Do you think the work of HeJus can contribute to ameliorate the doctoral researchers conditions inside Helmholtz Institutes?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;D:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Of Course it can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Yes, definitely! I think we’re on a good way there. It’s for sure not going to happen overnight, though, and we need more input and feedback from doctoral researchers at the institutions, most importantly via our survey happening in the beginning of 2017. I think we made it quite clear in the discussions with the responsible officials that we are the scientific future of the centers – and not just some cheap labor without a voice.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-do-you-think-the-hejus-could-be-an-example-for-other-researcher-in-other-institution-inside-and-outside-germany"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Do you think the HeJus could be an example for other researcher in other institution inside and outside Germany?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Another strong yes here. To my experience, it is very difficult to reach and mobilize doctoral researchers. So many people are complaining about their working conditions or their supervision, but in order change something we must team up! This part of our scientific career is the one phase where you basically should be as free as possible to realize your own ideas, but realistically seen, it is the time of highest dependency for most doctoral researchers. The things we do within Helmholtz also can help to motivate researchers to look beyond their everyday field of work, maybe encouraging to share ideas of science with the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-what-are-in-your-opinion-the-biggest-challenges-a-doctoral-researcher-has-to-face-in-his-3-5-years-at-the-helmholtz-institutes"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: What are in your opinion the biggest challenges a doctoral researcher has to face in his 3-5 years at the Helmholtz Institutes?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; The most common problems that have been revealed across the Helmholtz Association were: lack or poor supervision, depression, unclear contracts, unknown future. Of course all these problems and their magnitude and relevance differ between centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; For the “usual” researcher the most common challenge is simply how to finish the thesis project within the given timeframe, though that is barely worth noticing. That being said, all the other problems arising are often structural, i.e. insufficient funding or problems between supervisors and collaborators or even the classical clash between the professor and their doctoral researchers, due to missed chances for communication. It’s these issues that doctoral researcher representatives like the HeJus can make a difference in.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-how-could-hejus-help-and-contribute-to-solve-and-overcome-these-challenges"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: How could HeJus help and contribute to solve and overcome these challenges?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; As a Helmholtz Association PhD representation, we always try to work towards the improvement of the doctoral Researchers working conditions. Currently, we’re working on improving the contract situation across the Helmholtz Association. We want all doctoral researchers to feel secure and appreciated at all Helmholtz centers. Also, we’re in contact with Helmholtz Graduate Centre coordinators that have structures and closer connection with the doctoral researchers at the respective centres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;E:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; In my opinion, the strong dependency of doctoral researchers that I mentioned before is the reasons why Helmholtz Juniors are so important. As a joint network, we can focus much more on general structural problems and on how to solve them, than a single doctoral researcher or even local representatives could. Sure, I could always personally ask for a rise of my salary and be successful, but setting new standards in the field requires to bring forces together. A main strength of HeJu is the sharing of information – problems of doctoral researchers at one center might already have been solved at another. It is much easier to argue with officials about topics of concern for doctoral researchers when you can toss in information and experience from colleagues at completely different institutes. It worked pretty often in the last year.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-what-are-the-priorities-the-hejus-are-currently-working-on"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: What are the priorities the HeJus are currently working on?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Working conditions improvement, in particular of stipend holders. At the moment we are proposing an improved version of contracts that should be implemented across all 18 Helmholtz Centres. Also, the survey that is planned to be released soon, in the first months of 2017. This will give us an insight into working conditions situation across all Helmholtz Centres and supervision satisfaction amongst all doctoral researchers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; The top priorities are the survey, working conditions improvment and making the NextGen@Helmholtz 2017 in Kiel (Conference with doctoral researchers of all the Helmholtz centers) happen, in no particular order. There might be some novelties regarding joint projects with PhDNet and the Leibniz representation later this year. Stay tuned for more info on &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or Twitter &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;@HelmholtzJrs&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-what-do-you-think-of-the-raise-of-the-awareness-on-phd-frustrationdepression-science-wide-as-well-as-the-long-working-hours-outside-contracts-for-an-example-see-here"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: What do you think of the raise of the awareness on PhD frustration/depression science-wide, as well as the long working hours outside contracts (for an example see&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.nature.com/news/hard-work-little-reward-nature-readers-reveal-working-hours-and-research-challenges-1.20933?WT.mc_id=FBK_NA_1611_FHNEWSHARDWORKLITTLEREWARD_PORTFOLIO" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;)?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; The whole topic is slowly getting into the attention of media and the science community, which I think is superb, but as long as the “Old skool” Professors just regard this as weakness of a younger generation - À la: “In my PhD I did not even have time to count my working hours, let alone thing about holidays” - little will change. Perhaps, with such a high number of people considering quitting, one might wonder whether there really is a need for everyone to go through doing a PhD project (as it is still required for many jobs in Germany) or if a smaller number of well-connected and optimally supported researchers would be much more efficient. In the end, it’s a job that involves a lot of creativity and I am not sure if being forced to do more than 50 hours a week can really be kept throughout a whole career, without damaging motivation and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-how-do-you-think-we-could-improve-the-situation-in-the-helmholtz-centers-if-it-is-needed"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;How do you think we could improve the situation in the Helmholtz Centers, if it is needed?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I think we really must get rid of the old thinking of doctoral researchers doing work only for themselves and their education and shift the attention to the impact that our research has. We are working on proper scientific questions, we produce scientific output and by this we promote our Helmholtz Centers and science in Germany. It should be only natural to provide the best support for these highly-specialized workers, if we want to have the best institutions in the respective fields of study. And I think Helmholtz should have those aims for their centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="q-lastly-being-a-spokesperson-or-heju-could-be-perceived-as-a-lot-of-responsibility-and-work-would-you-tell-us-the-reason-why-you-like-it-and-dedicate-your-time-and-why-in-your-opinion-would-be-nice-for-other-researcher-to-join-the-hejus"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q: Lastly, being a spokesperson, or HeJu, could be perceived as a lot of responsibility and work. Would you tell us the reason why you like it and dedicate your time and why, in your opinion, would be nice for other researcher to join the HeJus?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Helmholtz Juniors positions are open for all enthusiastic volunteers researchers across Helmholtz Associated centres that are willing to work towards the improvement of PhD working conditions in general. We are welcoming anyone that has a need and drive to work for the PhD life improvement as a Helmholtz Junior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I am a spokesperson because, by doing this, I have the unique possibility to work with independent, young and skilful researchers on topics completely unrelated with our usual field of science. It is, basically, science seen from a different angle. I learned a great deal within this time and I am sure that I will be able to use these skills I have acquired through my whole life, though “doing the job” seems tiresome at times. We learn a lot doing our PhD anyways, but these extra lessons are worthwhile to be taken. It’s simply an incredibly stimulating way to spend your time and do something useful. You have my definite recommendation for anyone to join the Helmholtz Juniors! You won’t regret it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>