<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Reports on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/reports/</link><description>Recent content in Reports on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/reports/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Nachhaltige Spitzenforschung durch faire Arbeitsbedingungen</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/07/nachhaltige-spitzenforschung-durch-faire-arbeitsbedingungen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/07/nachhaltige-spitzenforschung-durch-faire-arbeitsbedingungen/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/07/nachhaltige-spitzenforschung-durch-faire-arbeitsbedingungen/images/Blog-banner.png" alt="Featured image of post Nachhaltige Spitzenforschung durch faire Arbeitsbedingungen" /&gt;&lt;h3 id="sustainable-cutting-edge-research-through-fair-working-conditions-the-necessity-of-transparent-collective-agreements-for-doctoral-researchers-in-the-helmholtz-association"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustainable Cutting-Edge Research through Fair Working Conditions: The&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Necessity of Transparent Collective Agreements for Doctoral Researchers in the Helmholtz Association&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recruiting top national and international talent is a major challenge in the highly competitive field of academic research and is of crucial importance to the Helmholtz Association of German Research Centres (HGF). To succeed in the race for scientific progress, the HGF must offer attractive and reliable working conditions for its early-career researchers. In practice, however, individual contracts are predominantly concluded between the respective Helmholtz Centers and doctoral researchers, which reduces both the transparency of contract terms and the equal opportunity goals pursued by the HGF. As the voice of doctoral researchers within the HGF, the Helmholtz Juniors advocate for integrating all doctoral researchers employed at Helmholtz Centers into the collective agreement for the public sector (TVöD), pay grade E13. This is the only way to ensure fair and transparent working conditions and attract top-tier talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following outlines the advantages of collective agreements over individual contracts, often referred to as funding agreements. In contrast, scholarships typically fail to provide the necessary social security and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-create-transparency"&gt;Collective Agreements Create Transparency
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Science, as an international field of work, requires regulations that are transparent and understandable in an international context1. In a statement on the amendment of the Act on Temporary Scientific Contracts (WissZeitVG), the Alliance of Science Organisations in Germany warned against the risk of a confusing diversity of regulations and, in the worst case, disparities between institutions2. The Max Planck Society, for example, offers at least standardized (funding) contracts, whereas the HGF features a remarkable diversity of contracts for doctoral researchers. The most common type of contract in the HGF is individual, non-tariff agreements with durations of two to four years and compensation ranging from 55% to 100% of a full-time position. Only about a third of the centers apply the TVöD on an individual basis. Despite having an application agreement with the United Services Union (ver.di), two Helmholtz Centers effectively exclude doctoral researchers from the collective agreement by invoking § 1 para. 2 letter s of the TVöD. Two other centers are affiliated with universities due to their historical development and therefore apply the collective agreement for the public service of the federal states (TV-L), which uses a different pay scale. This inconsistent and arbitrary patchwork of rules not only prevents transparency but also creates inequalities among doctoral researchers within the HGF. This undermines equal opportunity and makes working conditions difficult to understand from an international perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-ensure-equal-opportunity"&gt;Collective Agreements Ensure Equal Opportunity
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improving equal opportunity is a central priority in the HGF - this principle is firmly anchored in the HGF&amp;rsquo;s mission and is an integral part of its talent management3. Through their uniformity, collective agreements are an important tool that can significantly promote equal opportunity across the HGF. Collective agreements establish a standardized minimum framework that is regularly negotiated publicly and applies to all doctoral researchers. They ensure standardized regulations for working hours and vacation, recognize professional experience in compensation, and provide social security through additional benefits such as occupational pension schemes. In contrast, individual contracts can vary significantly in content and are subject to the unilateral stipulations of funding bodies, such as the Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space (BMFTR), formerly the Federal Ministry for Education and Research (BMBF), which define only maximum standards - allowing individual institutes to make downward deviations at their discretion. This opens the door to potential misuse and disadvantages for individual doctoral researchers. With collective bargaining, any changes to the agreement are automatically applied to all employment contracts. In contrast, individual contracts only reflect new rules in newly signed agreements. Thus, collective agreements ensure full transparency and lay the foundation for equal opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-increase-attractiveness-and-satisfaction"&gt;Collective Agreements Increase Attractiveness and Satisfaction
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sustainable and fair working conditions are not only key to long-term viability but also decisive for the lasting attractiveness and success of research institutions in an increasingly competitive academic landscape - a principle the Helmholtz Association already established in its 2016 sustainability management guidelines (LeNa). These guidelines emphasized the importance of developing new career paths and avoiding precarious employment, particularly for early-career researchers&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;4&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Competitive working conditions are the basis for attracting and retaining talented young scientists from both national and international backgrounds5,6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2020 study found that good working conditions and career prospects are key drivers of innovation in academic research7. Establishing good working conditions has twofold benefits: on the one hand, secure employment leads to higher satisfaction and productivity&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn4" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;8&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn4" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;; on the other hand, it enhances the employer’s appeal to international top talent. Job satisfaction is therefore a critical factor in the attractiveness of the public science sector. By introducing transparent, uniform contracts based on binding institutional application of the TVöD for doctoral researchers, the HGF can offer its early-career researchers sustainable, fair, and favorable working conditions - ensuring the retention of young talent amid a shortage of skilled workers in the public research sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-reduce-bureaucracy"&gt;Collective Agreements Reduce Bureaucracy
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2023 inflation compensation payment demonstrated that the diversity of contract types results in increased administrative workload and uncertainty among doctoral researchers. Introducing the collective agreement for all doctoral researchers would simplify administrative processes and create independence from the directives of funding bodies such as the BMFTR, since collective bargaining law overrides ministerial guidelines and authorizations. This benefits both researchers and administrative staff, fosters a coherent and efficient organizational structure, enhances transparency, and strengthens the Helmholtz Centers&amp;rsquo; appeal as employers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we emphasize that the binding institutional application of the TVöD without exception for all doctoral researchers at all Helmholtz Centers is a necessary measure. It aligns with the interests of the HGF by increasing its competitiveness in recruiting national and international talent, ensuring high satisfaction and productivity among researchers, promoting equal opportunity, and simplifying administrative processes. By supporting this initiative, the HGF can further strengthen its position as a leading actor in research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Helmholtz Juniors represent around 8,000 doctoral researchers within the Helmholtz Association. They advocate for the introduction of collective agreements for doctoral researchers across the entire Helmholtz Association of German Research Centres. This position was unanimously adopted at the Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting in 2024.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref1" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;1 - &lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref1" &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Helmholtz-Promotionsleitlinien (2019), online unter:           &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/upload_Karriere/190520_Helmholtz_Promotionsleitlinien_DE.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/upload_Karriere/190520_Helmholtz_Promotionsleitlinien_DE.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 - Allianz der Wissenschaftsorganisationen, Stellungnahme 27. März 2023: Für attraktive wissenschaftliche Karrieren in Deutschland,         online unter: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/200230616_Allianz-Kommentierung_Referentenentwurf-WissZeitVG_Wissenschaftskarrieren-ermoeglichen_fin-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Wissenschaftskarrieren ermöglichen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/200230616_Allianz-Kommentierung_Referentenentwurf-WissZeitVG_Wissenschaftskarrieren-ermoeglichen_fin-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;–&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/200230616_Allianz-Kommentierung_Referentenentwurf-WissZeitVG_Wissenschaftskarrieren-ermoeglichen_fin-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Kommentierung der Allianz der Wissenschaftsorganisationen zum WissZeitVG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 - Helmholtz Homepage, online unter: &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;www.helmholtz.de/ueber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;uns/wer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;wir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;sind/zahlen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;und&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;fakten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;neu/talentfoerderung,&lt;/a&gt; Stand 2024&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;4 -&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Ferretti, J. et al.: LeNa-Handreichung. Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement in außeruniversitären Forschungsorganisationen, 2016, online unter: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/LeNa-Leitfaden_Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement_2016.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/LeNa-Leitfaden_Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement_2016.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 - Barcan, R. (2018). Paying dearly for privilege: conceptions, experiences and temporalities of vocation in academic life. &lt;em&gt;Pedagogy,&lt;/em&gt;        &lt;em&gt;Culture &amp;amp; Society,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;26&lt;/em&gt;, 105-121. &lt;a class="link" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14681366.2017.1358207" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/14681366.2017.1358207&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 - Reymert, I., Vabø, A., Borlaug, S.B. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2023). Barriers to attracting the best researchers: perceptions of academics in economics       and physics in three European countries. &lt;em&gt;High Educ&lt;/em&gt; 86, 1173–1193 (2023). &lt;a class="link" href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10734-022-00967-w" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10734-022-00967-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref3" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;7 -&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref3" &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Castellacci, F., &amp;amp; Viñas-Bardolet, C. (2020). Permanent contracts and job satisfaction in academia: evidence from European      countries. Studies in Higher Education, 46(9), 1866–1880. &lt;a class="link" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03075079.2019.1711041" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/03075079.2019.1711041&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 - Bryson, Alex and Forth, John and Stokes, Lucy, Does Worker Wellbeing Affect Workplace Performance? IZA Discussion Paper No. 9096, Available at SSRN: &lt;a class="link" href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=2655044" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://ssrn.com/abstract=2655044&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="link" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2655044" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2655044&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/images/interview-2.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weather you are currently thinking of doing a PhD or you are already a doctoral  researcher (DR), it might always quite interesting to know how is it like to be a doctoral researcher at the largest scientific organization in Germany. More specifically, how are DRs networked? How diverse are DRs? or to be of most interest of many of you, how well is a DR being paid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our newest survey (report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  ), we have (as always) put these points into perspective and asked our DRs what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center. Below, our survey team will tell you some of the key results from the survey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sY_L269sST4"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors and N^2 at the March for Science</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/05/helmholtz-juniors-and-n2-at-the-march-for-science/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/05/helmholtz-juniors-and-n2-at-the-march-for-science/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2017/05/helmholtz-juniors-and-n2-at-the-march-for-science/images/Berlin.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors and N^2 at the March for Science" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today we have a second guest post by Tatyana Dubich, the Speaker of the Helmholtz Juniors Communication Group and a doctoral researcher at The Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz-hzi.de/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZI&lt;/a&gt;). Enjoy the interviews with the participants of the March for Science!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;March for Science, not march of scientists&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among all the things said and published every day, it might be hard to tell where the truth is: astrology or astronomy, creationism or evolutionism, homeopathy or medicine.  The answer, however, is simple: the one, which has real evidence! On Saturday, the 22nd of April, people all over the world joined the &lt;a class="link" href="https://satellites.marchforscience.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;strong&gt;March for Science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to state it once again. People, who believe in science, joined marches in more than 600 cities worldwide including Germany to demonstrate importance of free, unbiased, evidence-based science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The March for Science was supported by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/ueber_uns/die_gemeinschaft/standpunkte/allianz_der_wissenschaftsorganisationen/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Alliance of Science Organisations in Germany&lt;/a&gt;, which includes the Helmholtz Association. In its official statement, the Alliance says that “anti-democratic and anti-scientific actions and currents, led by political decision-makers or populist movements, threaten the work and the values of the sciences and all those who work in it”. The statement also advocated the importance of freedom in research and teaching. At the centers level, Prof. Dr. Karin Lochte, Director of &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.awi.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Alfred Wegener Institute, Helmholtz Centre for Polar and Marine Research (AWI)&lt;/a&gt;, said in her &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.awi.de/nc/ueber-uns/service/presse/pressemeldung/alfred-wegener-institut-unterstuetzt-march-for-science.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; that “science thrives on the freedom of opinion, on tolerance and international exchange, and on the shared goal of understanding the world we live in and using peaceful means to make it just a bit better every single day”, and motivated everyone to fight for the freedom in research as both scientists and citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
\[gallery type="slideshow" size="full" ids="380,382,383"\]&lt;p&gt;Despite the caprice April weather, people who support science marched along the main streets of their cities, carrying wonderful homemade banners. “Science, not silence” was written on many of them. Helmholtz Juniors joined the marches in Berlin, Hamburg, Heidelberg, Munich, Dresden and Göttingen, and they motivated all the doctoral researches within the Helmholtz Association to join. We marched in a friendly crowd as &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs/status/839768720243322880" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;N^2 - the newly formed network between Helmholtz Juniors, Max Plank PhDnet and Leibniz PhD Network&lt;/a&gt;. We carried the N^2 logo and our slogans, urging to “make the Earth cool again” and pointing out that “we are p&amp;lt;0.05”!&lt;/p&gt;
\[gallery type="slideshow" size="full" link="file" ids="402,406,398,389"\]&lt;p&gt;In Berlin, Heidelberg and Munich marches were accompanied by speeches from academics of different levels (from students to institutes&amp;rsquo; directors), policymakers and science communicators. The talks pointed at the importance of evidence-based decision making for further development; why it is crucial to support  free, unbiased, evidence-based science. After all, science shapes almost every aspects of our everyday life and it is the key to progress.&lt;/p&gt;
\[gallery type="slideshow" link="file" size="full" ids="392,399,409,404,403,401,407,405"\]&lt;p&gt;HeJu Communication Team asked the march participants in Berlin, Heidelberg and Munich: why did they march for Science? Most of them joined to show that they believe in fact-based thinking in contrast to recent trends of emotion-based thinking, that is leading to decreased number of vaccinations, climate-change denial, and the use of &amp;ldquo;alternative facts&amp;rdquo; in politics, to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the interviewed comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“After all what happened in the last years in America and Europe it is important to show the world that  there are people who believe in science and don’t want to believe in alternative facts, like all the movements against vaccination, evolution and those kind of things. Because what happens in science is the truth and we have much more evidence. With a march like this we can convince people to believe in facts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I hope, that events like this will make a difference. I cannot hope to make the difference alone, but rather a part of a big scientific community.  We, as a community, should show that we are against cutting the budget for research, which has a major impact on our future. I think it is very important to address this topics and make people think about it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I march for science because I believe, that we should stay together and remember, that we are not in the Middle ages anymore. Therefore, we should support scientists to explore our world for further development”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The decisions should be made based on evidence, not on feelings. We came here to stress that.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I think it is important that we stand up for the integrity of science and openness. It is important that scientist can do their research without restrictions by government or people, driven by feelings”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I came here to stress the importance of science without politic. Science should be free from political influence”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the participants had different reasons, but one common goal - to underline the importance of staying rational and objective rather than following feelings. And we all hope that the March for Science will make a difference. But the march was just the beginning. We should keep the momentum and advocate good science. Communicating science, making it seen and heard should be our everyday goal and not a one-off deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join the movement!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>