<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Survey on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/survey/</link><description>Recent content in Survey on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/survey/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Exposing the problem</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health.png" alt="Featured image of post HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Exposing the problem" /&gt;&lt;h3 id="mental-health--why-do-we-care"&gt;Mental Health – Why do we care?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mental health of Doctoral Researchers has been increasingly analysed during the last years, often with alarming results. Major concerns regarding the well-being of early career researchers are depression, anxiety, harassment and a difficult work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do studies say?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Graduate Assembly (2014) reported that 47% of Doctoral Researchers of the University of California, Berkeley met the threshold for depression. A recent study by Levecque et al. (2017) analysed the situation of more than 3000 Doctoral Researchers in Belgium and found that the risk for psychiatric disorders in academia is higher than in other highly-educated groups. 32% of Doctoral Researchers are at risk of a common psychiatric disorder, such as depression. Main reasons were work-family interfaces, job demands and job control, and the leadership style of the supervisor (Levecque et al., 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Nature study, 29% of 5700 Doctoral Researchers listed mental health as an area of concern, with half of them getting help for depression or anxiety caused by their PhD study (Woolston, 2017). A follow-up Nature study in 2019 showed that things seem to get worse; 36% of 6300 PhDs from all around the globe seeking help for depression and anxiety related to their PhD project. Also, one-fifth reported bullying, while another fifth experienced discrimination or harassment (Nature, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EPFL Doctoral III survey (2019) draws a similar image, 20.7% of the 1043 participating Doctoral Researchers experienced &lt;strong&gt;bullying&lt;/strong&gt; or behaviours that may constitute as bullying, which includes aggressive behaviour, being undermined and being isolated and ignored by people at work. Symptoms of depression were associated with experienced bullying behaviour. If there is evidence of bullying more than 90% of respondents showed depressive symptoms (EPFL, 2019). Another reason for the critical mental health situation is that success is measured in publications, citations, funding and impact. The autonomy of research is reduced or removed when funding, publications and impact are part of the universities formal monitoring and evaluation system, and when supervisors judge the failure or success of Doctoral Researchers (Nature, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did we find?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/power-abuse.png"
width="357"
height="624"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/power-abuse_hu_372919eba0264d67.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/power-abuse_hu_8f41315090e3c21f.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="57"
data-flex-basis="137px"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health.png"
width="482"
height="624"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health_hu_1c4a440b0244b746.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-exposing-the-problem/images/mental-health_hu_88639f2007bcde78.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="77"
data-flex-basis="185px"
&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 2019 Helmholtz Juniors survey, we tried to get an overview of the mental health of all Doctoral Researchers within the Helmholtz Association. The survey used a shortened STAI questionnaire. The high number of working hours - 66 % work more than 41h while even 18 % work more than 50 h a week - and high conflict potential - 16 % reported conflicts with superiors are critical influences on the mental health of young Doctoral Researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the questionnaire indicated 22 % showed signs of moderate to severe depression and 70 % showed signs of moderate to high state anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are, sadly, similar to the findings of the already presented studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the first step on finding solutions and ways to tackle a problem is knowing about it in the first place!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We´re working on various strategies, as Helmholtz Juniors on our own, as well as in joined projects with individual centres and of course with the Helmholtz Association’s Headquarters in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And we would like to hear your opinion on that topic!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think are the biggest challenges for keeping a good mental Healh while doing your PhD or in science in general?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you encountered a hostile workplace atmosphere?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want to help us create a more sustainable work environment in academic research?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We would love to hear your thoughts and ideas!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>NextGen 2016: More than a Conference!</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today, we have a special guest post by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Danja_Sarink" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Danja Sarink&lt;/a&gt;, PhD Candidate at the Division of Cancer Epidemiology, The German Cancer Research Center (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.dkfz.de/en/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;DKFZ&lt;/a&gt;). Danja is also the spokesperson of the Survey Group of the HeJus. Now I leave you with a brilliant inside look at NextGen 2016!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 28-30 September Helmholtz Juniors hosted the very first NextGen@Helmholtz conference. Nearly &lt;strong&gt;120 doctoral researchers&lt;/strong&gt; from all Helmholtz centers joined us for action-packed: three days of networking, presenting and learning, at &lt;strong&gt;the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz-hzi.de/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research&lt;/a&gt; in Braunschweig&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an impression of the conference have a look!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RxE0eGhc_Tw"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did we do?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Represent-your-Institute-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Represent-your-Institute-300x200_hu_533d9b0f4113a375.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Represent-your-Institute-300x200_hu_7bdf49dcad341e38.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="NextGen 2016 Represent Your Institute"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start the conference and to introduce all 18 Helmholtz Centers participants &lt;strong&gt;presented their institute in one minute&lt;/strong&gt;. We got a fantastic overview of the huge diversity of research going on in the Helmholtz Association – and the creativity of PhD students! Who knew that umbrellas make excellent jellyfish? And that maybe, next time, we should take into account when Oktoberfest happens!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main focus points of NextGen was &lt;strong&gt;multidisciplinary&lt;/strong&gt; and we challenged participants to explain their work to doctoral researchers from different fields; 83 participants presented their research in three poster sessions. There was naturally a lot of discussion between researchers from similar fields, but the amount of crosstalk – physicists explaining their work to sociologists, engineers asking about the work of geologists, and so on – was amazing to see!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa Bittner (Influence of pH on the toxicity of pharmaceuticals in zebrafish embryos, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.ufz.de/index.php?en=33573" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;UFZ&lt;/a&gt;), Mia Rudolph (Serial Protein Crystallography in Living Cells, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.desy.de/index_eng.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;DESY&lt;/a&gt;) and Uli Einhaus (ROPPERI-A TPC readout with Timepix and pads, DESY) did an especially great job explaining their work, and received the &lt;strong&gt;poster awards&lt;/strong&gt;. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six truly brave doctoral researchers participated in the &lt;strong&gt;NextGen Science Slam&lt;/strong&gt;, and we saw some really innovative takes on science – appealing to participants’ empathy, sense of humor and sense of rhythm. We have to give a honorable mention the impressive rap from UFZ’s very own McBiogas (Fabian Bonk), but the audience awarded the best science slam to Daniel Meza Arredondo from HZB, who talked about mom, Pesos and a chocolate vending machine on Mexikoplatz in Berlin, which was an excellent analogy for his work on solar cells. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, at this point, everyone at NextGen knew all about the Helmholtz Association and how to present their doctoral work – &lt;strong&gt;but what comes after&lt;/strong&gt;? The classical path of doctorate-postdoc-professor is of course not nearly the only option for a doctoral researcher and the alumni session offered the opportunity for participants to talk to Helmholtz alumni about their career paths. The 12 alumni who joined were all at different stages in their careers – anywhere between postdoc and retired – and some had taken surprising career paths to get to their current jobs in various sectors, ranging from academia to science communication, to technology and product management in industry, to entrepreneurship and politics. The round tables were swamped and alumni spoke to participants to the absolute end of the session and, for those who could stay, even after the session ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alumni session was followed (after an amazing lunch) by a multidisciplinary workshop, where carefully randomized teams of doctoral researchers from all Helmholtz centers were put on the spot: &lt;strong&gt;how could humanity travel to and survive on Mars?&lt;/strong&gt; Every team was required to include all their members fields in their mission plan, but we kept other parameters for this task deliberately vague (will earth still be there to go back to? Will space travel exist?). Seven teams presented very varied takes and some very convincing reasoning on this challenge – a focus on the journey to Mars versus what to do on Mars, keeping the space craft operational versus using it for resources, living above ground versus living below, relying on trade versus Mars’ own resources. One of the most important tools for success is of course using the skills of everyone involved, and proposals were judged as such by Dr. Rebecca Ludwig, project manager with the cross-disciplinary &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.enlight-ten.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;ENLIGHT-TEN&lt;/a&gt; program. For missions this big, there can only be one winning proposal – Congratulations to the ingenious crew of M.Pathfinder!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, NextGen hosted an &lt;strong&gt;expert panel on the topic of “publish or perish”&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/ueber_uns/die_gemeinschaft/praesident/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Wiestler&lt;/a&gt; (President of the Helmholtz Association), &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.jacobs-university.de/directory/alerchl" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Alexander Lerchl&lt;/a&gt; (Jacobs University Bremen), &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz-hzi.de/en/research/research_topics/anti_infectives/chemical_biology/mark_broenstrup/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Mark Brönstrup&lt;/a&gt; (HZI Braunschweig), and &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.icm.tu-bs.de/%7Ebeick/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Bettina Eick&lt;/a&gt; (TU Braunschweig). It was a great experience to listen to professionals talking about the broad topic, its influence on their fields of research, and how it relates to doctoral researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did we do well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two thirds of the participants completed our &lt;strong&gt;exit-survey&lt;/strong&gt;, and results were overwhelmingly positive! Nearly all participants rated NextGen@Helmholtz as very good (62%) or good (34%), and a stunning 88% would recommend it to others. The science slam (68% very good; 21% good) and alumni sessions (49% very good; 35% good) were rated as highlights of the program. Opinions on the poster session, multidisciplinary workshop, and expert panel were a bit more divided – though they were still rated as good or very good by at least half of the participants. The time available for and facilitation of networking (social activities, workshops, etc) during the conference were also well received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Picture1-2-1000x309.png"
width="1000"
height="309"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Picture1-2-1000x309_hu_bebeffaef2576b95.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Picture1-2-1000x309_hu_b1dfa579319a4f09.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="NextGen 2016 Exit Survey"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="323"
data-flex-basis="776px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are always things that could have gone better, and that we will of course aim to improve! The two points participants liked least were the venue for the poster session (5% very poor; 19% poor) and the time available for the multidisciplinary workshops (7% very poor; 24% poor[1]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A big “thank you!” to…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to extend a big “Thank you!” to the Helmholtz Association for making it possible for us to organize NextGen@Helmholtz, the Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research (HZI) in Braunschweig for hosting us, and to all speakers and participants for making it a success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s next for NextGen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope NextGen@Helmholtz will continue to provide an informal and low pressure environment for doctoral researchers to talk and gain ideas about their science and their PhD (and beyond), and to try new approaches to presenting their work, both regarding new formats and people from completely unrelated fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep an eye out for NextGen@Helmholtz 2017 at the Helmholtz Centre for Ocean Research (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.geomar.de/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;GEOMAR&lt;/a&gt;) in Kiel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Gruppe.jpg"
width="999"
height="562"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Gruppe_hu_b0a258582c9019c9.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Gruppe_hu_290ef867c91881b6.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="NextGen 2016 Group Picture"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="177"
data-flex-basis="426px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Excluding 33 participants (42%) who did not answer this question&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>