<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Helmholtz on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/helmholtz/</link><description>Recent content in Helmholtz on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/helmholtz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/images/interview-2.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weather you are currently thinking of doing a PhD or you are already a doctoral  researcher (DR), it might always quite interesting to know how is it like to be a doctoral researcher at the largest scientific organization in Germany. More specifically, how are DRs networked? How diverse are DRs? or to be of most interest of many of you, how well is a DR being paid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our newest survey (report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  ), we have (as always) put these points into perspective and asked our DRs what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center. Below, our survey team will tell you some of the key results from the survey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sY_L269sST4"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>NextGen 2016: More than a Conference!</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today, we have a special guest post by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Danja_Sarink" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Danja Sarink&lt;/a&gt;, PhD Candidate at the Division of Cancer Epidemiology, The German Cancer Research Center (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.dkfz.de/en/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;DKFZ&lt;/a&gt;). Danja is also the spokesperson of the Survey Group of the HeJus. Now I leave you with a brilliant inside look at NextGen 2016!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 28-30 September Helmholtz Juniors hosted the very first NextGen@Helmholtz conference. Nearly &lt;strong&gt;120 doctoral researchers&lt;/strong&gt; from all Helmholtz centers joined us for action-packed: three days of networking, presenting and learning, at &lt;strong&gt;the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz-hzi.de/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research&lt;/a&gt; in Braunschweig&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an impression of the conference have a look!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RxE0eGhc_Tw"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did we do?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Represent-your-Institute-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Represent-your-Institute-300x200_hu_533d9b0f4113a375.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Represent-your-Institute-300x200_hu_7bdf49dcad341e38.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="NextGen 2016 Represent Your Institute"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start the conference and to introduce all 18 Helmholtz Centers participants &lt;strong&gt;presented their institute in one minute&lt;/strong&gt;. We got a fantastic overview of the huge diversity of research going on in the Helmholtz Association – and the creativity of PhD students! Who knew that umbrellas make excellent jellyfish? And that maybe, next time, we should take into account when Oktoberfest happens!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main focus points of NextGen was &lt;strong&gt;multidisciplinary&lt;/strong&gt; and we challenged participants to explain their work to doctoral researchers from different fields; 83 participants presented their research in three poster sessions. There was naturally a lot of discussion between researchers from similar fields, but the amount of crosstalk – physicists explaining their work to sociologists, engineers asking about the work of geologists, and so on – was amazing to see!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa Bittner (Influence of pH on the toxicity of pharmaceuticals in zebrafish embryos, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.ufz.de/index.php?en=33573" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;UFZ&lt;/a&gt;), Mia Rudolph (Serial Protein Crystallography in Living Cells, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.desy.de/index_eng.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;DESY&lt;/a&gt;) and Uli Einhaus (ROPPERI-A TPC readout with Timepix and pads, DESY) did an especially great job explaining their work, and received the &lt;strong&gt;poster awards&lt;/strong&gt;. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six truly brave doctoral researchers participated in the &lt;strong&gt;NextGen Science Slam&lt;/strong&gt;, and we saw some really innovative takes on science – appealing to participants’ empathy, sense of humor and sense of rhythm. We have to give a honorable mention the impressive rap from UFZ’s very own McBiogas (Fabian Bonk), but the audience awarded the best science slam to Daniel Meza Arredondo from HZB, who talked about mom, Pesos and a chocolate vending machine on Mexikoplatz in Berlin, which was an excellent analogy for his work on solar cells. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, at this point, everyone at NextGen knew all about the Helmholtz Association and how to present their doctoral work – &lt;strong&gt;but what comes after&lt;/strong&gt;? The classical path of doctorate-postdoc-professor is of course not nearly the only option for a doctoral researcher and the alumni session offered the opportunity for participants to talk to Helmholtz alumni about their career paths. The 12 alumni who joined were all at different stages in their careers – anywhere between postdoc and retired – and some had taken surprising career paths to get to their current jobs in various sectors, ranging from academia to science communication, to technology and product management in industry, to entrepreneurship and politics. The round tables were swamped and alumni spoke to participants to the absolute end of the session and, for those who could stay, even after the session ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alumni session was followed (after an amazing lunch) by a multidisciplinary workshop, where carefully randomized teams of doctoral researchers from all Helmholtz centers were put on the spot: &lt;strong&gt;how could humanity travel to and survive on Mars?&lt;/strong&gt; Every team was required to include all their members fields in their mission plan, but we kept other parameters for this task deliberately vague (will earth still be there to go back to? Will space travel exist?). Seven teams presented very varied takes and some very convincing reasoning on this challenge – a focus on the journey to Mars versus what to do on Mars, keeping the space craft operational versus using it for resources, living above ground versus living below, relying on trade versus Mars’ own resources. One of the most important tools for success is of course using the skills of everyone involved, and proposals were judged as such by Dr. Rebecca Ludwig, project manager with the cross-disciplinary &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.enlight-ten.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;ENLIGHT-TEN&lt;/a&gt; program. For missions this big, there can only be one winning proposal – Congratulations to the ingenious crew of M.Pathfinder!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, NextGen hosted an &lt;strong&gt;expert panel on the topic of “publish or perish”&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/ueber_uns/die_gemeinschaft/praesident/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Wiestler&lt;/a&gt; (President of the Helmholtz Association), &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.jacobs-university.de/directory/alerchl" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Alexander Lerchl&lt;/a&gt; (Jacobs University Bremen), &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz-hzi.de/en/research/research_topics/anti_infectives/chemical_biology/mark_broenstrup/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Mark Brönstrup&lt;/a&gt; (HZI Braunschweig), and &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.icm.tu-bs.de/%7Ebeick/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Prof. Bettina Eick&lt;/a&gt; (TU Braunschweig). It was a great experience to listen to professionals talking about the broad topic, its influence on their fields of research, and how it relates to doctoral researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did we do well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two thirds of the participants completed our &lt;strong&gt;exit-survey&lt;/strong&gt;, and results were overwhelmingly positive! Nearly all participants rated NextGen@Helmholtz as very good (62%) or good (34%), and a stunning 88% would recommend it to others. The science slam (68% very good; 21% good) and alumni sessions (49% very good; 35% good) were rated as highlights of the program. Opinions on the poster session, multidisciplinary workshop, and expert panel were a bit more divided – though they were still rated as good or very good by at least half of the participants. The time available for and facilitation of networking (social activities, workshops, etc) during the conference were also well received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Picture1-2-1000x309.png"
width="1000"
height="309"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Picture1-2-1000x309_hu_bebeffaef2576b95.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Picture1-2-1000x309_hu_b1dfa579319a4f09.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="NextGen 2016 Exit Survey"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="323"
data-flex-basis="776px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are always things that could have gone better, and that we will of course aim to improve! The two points participants liked least were the venue for the poster session (5% very poor; 19% poor) and the time available for the multidisciplinary workshops (7% very poor; 24% poor[1]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A big “thank you!” to…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to extend a big “Thank you!” to the Helmholtz Association for making it possible for us to organize NextGen@Helmholtz, the Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research (HZI) in Braunschweig for hosting us, and to all speakers and participants for making it a success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s next for NextGen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope NextGen@Helmholtz will continue to provide an informal and low pressure environment for doctoral researchers to talk and gain ideas about their science and their PhD (and beyond), and to try new approaches to presenting their work, both regarding new formats and people from completely unrelated fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep an eye out for NextGen@Helmholtz 2017 at the Helmholtz Centre for Ocean Research (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.geomar.de/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;GEOMAR&lt;/a&gt;) in Kiel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Gruppe.jpg"
width="999"
height="562"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Gruppe_hu_b0a258582c9019c9.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/11/nextgen-2016-more-than-a-conference/images/Gruppe_hu_290ef867c91881b6.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="NextGen 2016 Group Picture"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="177"
data-flex-basis="426px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Excluding 33 participants (42%) who did not answer this question&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting 2015 in Bremerhaven</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/Helmholtz-Juniors_FB-scaled.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting 2015 in Bremerhaven" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year’s annual meeting of the Helmholtz Juniors took place at the Alfred-Wegener-Institut (AWI) from the 14th to the 16th of January. New Helmholtz Juniors were introduced. We re-formed our working groups, elected new speakers and had interesting discussions and a nice time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/Helmholtz-Juniors_FB-1000x866.jpg"
width="1000"
height="866"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/Helmholtz-Juniors_FB-1000x866_hu_5d2ffa28b644da8e.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/Helmholtz-Juniors_FB-1000x866_hu_171a9ccac5a1be7a.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The Helmholtz Juniors of 2015 at the Alfred-Wegener-Institut"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="115"
data-flex-basis="277px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday afternoon, the last year’s speakers Nicholas Engel and Sripriya Murthy welcomed the previous and new Helmholtz Juniors to the meeting. The speakers of last year’s working groups presented their work and achievements and suggested topics for 2015. The survey group has finished the first evaluation of the 2014 survey. The evaluation is currently discussed and will be released roughly within the next two months. Further groups are “communication”, “event”, “working conditions” and “steadification”. See our homepage (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/hejus" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;www.helmholtz.de/hejus&lt;/a&gt;) for details on these groups. In the evening, the new Helmholtz Juniors chose their working groups. The groups of 2014 will be kept in 2015 and no new ones were established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/IMG_0021-300x225.jpg"
width="300"
height="225"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/IMG_0021-300x225_hu_365913c1c6cf5a9d.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/IMG_0021-300x225_hu_5cd49da98e3078a2.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Prof. Karin Lochte, director of the Alfred-Wegener-Institut, talks to the Helmholtz-Juniors"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/DSCN1492_small-300x225.jpg"
width="300"
height="225"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/DSCN1492_small-300x225_hu_bb5d163670cced9d.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/DSCN1492_small-300x225_hu_b005324cae53c977.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Presentation of the POLMAR graduate school by Claudia Hanfland and discussion on the situation and importance of graduate schools within the Helmholtz Association"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day started with a talk of Karin Lochte, head of the Alfred-Wegener-Institut, followed by a question and discussion session with her. After taking our group picture (the cover picture of the entry) we got a guided tour on the work of the AWI. Before lunch we met with Claudia Hanfland who coordinates the POLMAR graduate school (polmar.awi.de) and currently represents all Helmholtz graduate schools as their speaker. We discussed about the relevance of graduate schools and their function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, we had group working sessions in which the previous group’s speakers handed over their work to the new members. The first hours of group work were quite productive and we collected lots of new ideas and plans for 2015. Have a look on the picture of our group work sessions below!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_working_conditions_DSCN1505-scaled.jpg"
width="2560"
height="1920"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_working_conditions_DSCN1505-scaled_hu_cbfc96079a6536fc.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_working_conditions_DSCN1505-scaled_hu_6d66ebab6ea52adc.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Working Conditions Working Group"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_survey_DSCN1503-scaled.jpg"
width="2560"
height="1920"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_survey_DSCN1503-scaled_hu_c7ccc930ef79e962.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_survey_DSCN1503-scaled_hu_183c705185091570.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Survey Working Group"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_communication_DSCN1508-scaled.jpg"
width="2560"
height="1920"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_communication_DSCN1508-scaled_hu_57f1c4e2acbcceb.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_communication_DSCN1508-scaled_hu_bcaa902d6959107.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Communication Working Group"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_event_DSCN1506-scaled.jpg"
width="1920"
height="2560"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_event_DSCN1506-scaled_hu_d8d06a4c92d44cd4.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_event_DSCN1506-scaled_hu_f9acf6c974abbb32.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Event Working Group"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="75"
data-flex-basis="180px"
&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_stratefication_DSCN1507-scaled.jpg"
width="2560"
height="1920"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_stratefication_DSCN1507-scaled_hu_46a44882cd99810.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_stratefication_DSCN1507-scaled_hu_66258e5bd49d0ebf.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Stratefication Working Group"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started on Friday with group working sessions and with electing group speakers. After that Xixi Feng presented PhDnet (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.phdnet.mpg.de" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;www.phdnet.mpg.de&lt;/a&gt;) which is the PhD candidate representation of the Max Planck Society. She is one of the speakers of PhDnet. There are some intersections in the topics on which HeJu and PhDnet work such as regular contracts instead of scholarships. Therefore we started sending speakers to each other’s annual meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/DSCN1527_fb_new_heju_speakers-300x225.jpg"
width="300"
height="225"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/DSCN1527_fb_new_heju_speakers-300x225_hu_7417fbd92cfe9c48.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/DSCN1527_fb_new_heju_speakers-300x225_hu_3d25b80d074f0edf.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Speaker Picture, from left to right: Nicholas Engel (HeJu Speaker 2014), Xixi Feng (Stearing Group PhDnet), Meike Köhler (HeJu Speaker 2015) and Daniel Neumann (HeJu Speaker 2015)"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last points on the agenda were the elections for the two HeJu speakers of 2015 and the decision on the location for the next year’s annual meeting. Daniel Neumann (Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht) and Meike Köhler (Helmholtz Zentrum München) were elected as speakers. The next year’s meeting will take place at the Deutsches Zentrum für Luft- und Raumfahrt (DLR) in Oberpfaffenhofen, close to Munich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_thank_to_renate_DSCN1524-300x225.jpg"
width="300"
height="225"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_thank_to_renate_DSCN1524-300x225_hu_c112227af4a2b617.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/helmholtz-juniors-annual-meeting-2015-in-bremerhaven/images/fb_thank_to_renate_DSCN1524-300x225_hu_ee21f1eae4ec9017.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Renate Degen (left) gets a present from Meike Köhler (right) for organising the annual meeting in Bremerhaven."
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="133"
data-flex-basis="320px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank Renate Degen very much for organising the event in Bremerhaven. Also, we would like to thank the Helmholtz Association and the Alfred-Wegener-Institut very much for their financial support and for offering a location.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>