<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Berlin on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/berlin/</link><description>Recent content in Berlin on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/berlin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/images/LOGO_Blue2.png" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On July 13, the Helmholtz Juniors (you may know as HeJus) conducted their meeting in Berlin, which lasted for two days. More than 30 Juniors came from Helmholtz Centers all over Germany to join the Midterm Meeting taking place at the Helmholtz Association’s Headquarters (HGF) in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For weeks before the meeting, the Juniors were preparing the agenda and gathering information across all centers and the HeJus working groups on the working conditions of PhD students and also the major problems that the students at each center are facing. The agenda of the Midterm Meeting included discussions on the PhD contract model that HeJus Working Conditions group has been working on, and a session by &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.southampton.ac.uk/oes/postgraduate/research_students/km1g14.page" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Kyle Mayers&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Southampton on the British doctoral system. The agenda also included the ongoing preparations for the soon coming Helmholtz PhD conference “&lt;a class="link" href="https://indico.scc.kit.edu/indico/event/229/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;NextGen@Helmholtz&lt;/a&gt;” taking place this September at HZI in Braunschweig. The HeJus met up with the new members joining this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank you for following our live updates via &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and for your comments. Stay tuned for more details on the meeting&amp;rsquo;s recommendations!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Mid-Term Meeting 2015 in Berlin</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med2.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Mid-Term Meeting 2015 in Berlin" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th and 21st of July, the Helmholtz Juniors Mid-Term Meeting took place at the Helmholtz Association&amp;rsquo;s Head Office (HGF) in Berlin. It was the second Mid-Term Meeting ever and proved to be a great opportunity to meet each other again, to discuss the latest progress and problems, and to improve the cooperation of the Helmholtz Juniors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the first day of the meeting, we were welcomed by Caroline Krüger from the Helmholtz head office. The working phase was opened up with presentations from all Helmholtz Juniors working groups on the activities of the last half year and on future plans for the upcoming half year. Afterwards two guests from the Helmholtz Head Office gave a parallel session on two of the main topics we deal with. Elsbeth Lesner was guest of a discussion round on working conditions, PhD contracts and stipends. Jennifer Schevardo gave a firm presentation on different networks within the Helmholtz Community with a focus on the new “Helmholtz &amp;amp; Friends” Alumni network. “Helmholtz &amp;amp; Friends” aims to strengthen the Helmholtz-Feeling within the Association and initiates the build-up of a new network of peers that provide exchange of knowledge basically concentrating on social skills and leadership (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/helmholtz_friends/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz &amp;amp; Friends&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med-300x200_hu_ba9d877df27e559e.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4547_med-300x200_hu_73c72265f989b0b5.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Helmholtz Juniors at the Helmholtz Association’s Head Office in Berlin"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch – a delicious one by the way – our next guest was Sabine Helling-Moegen, the administrative head of the German Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases (DZNE). She gave a brief overview of the history of the German “Großforschungseinrichtungen” and of the the Helmholtz Association and described the process from narrow research topics towards nowadays program oriented research and the program oriented funding (“Programmorientierte Förderung”, POF). The interesting talk and the following discussion gave us the opportunity to gain a better understanding of mechanisms and politics in science and education in general and in the Helmholtz Association, in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last part of the first day was dedicated to a discussion on an overall strategy of the Helmholtz Juniors and on tasks for upcoming half year and their priority:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focus for the working conditions group: reduce number of in-house stipends and increase number of vacation days to 28 or 30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve the motivation of all PhD students to be part in the local PhD representative initiatives and in the Helmholtz Juniors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enhance visibility of the Helmholtz Juniors: Only if we are visible, we can change something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strengthen the connection to the HGF head office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strengthen our network to other groups which work for improving working conditions in science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve continuity after handover to new Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first day was concluded with dinner in a nice restaurant in Berlin‘s center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4515_med-300x200.jpg"
width="300"
height="200"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4515_med-300x200_hu_c1c8fb1f4d714433.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/07/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2015-in-berlin/images/DSCF4515_med-300x200_hu_8ce64420117126d4.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Discussing the Helmholtz Junior’s future plans"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day of our Mid-term meeting was dedicated towards group work. The working conditions group recapitulated their meeting with Elsbeth Lesner from the previous day. The Event group started planning a Helmholtz PhD day which should take place in 2016. Both, the Survey and the Communications working groups attended an Q&amp;amp;A session with Jan-Martin Wiarda, Bianca Berlin and Janine Tychsen from the Helmholtz Communications and Media Relations Office. The three of them were faced with several questions on internal and external communication issues. Besides receiving useful answers, possible contacts for our communication-related issues, and insight into the current projects of their group, we were encouraged to raise a critical voice inside and outside of the Helmholtz Association whenever necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a wrap-up and a basket of tasks for the upcoming months, we finished our Mid-term meeting in the early afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we, the Helmholtz Juniors, want to thank all our guests, the Helmholtz Association&amp;rsquo;s Head Office and the events working group. The meeting was a great success and will motivate us and enhance our future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>