<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Working-Conditions on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/working-conditions/</link><description>Recent content in Working-Conditions on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/working-conditions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-2/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-doctoral-researcher-at-a-helmholtz-center/images/interview-2.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (2/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weather you are currently thinking of doing a PhD or you are already a doctoral  researcher (DR), it might always quite interesting to know how is it like to be a doctoral researcher at the largest scientific organization in Germany. More specifically, how are DRs networked? How diverse are DRs? or to be of most interest of many of you, how well is a DR being paid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our newest survey (report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;  ), we have (as always) put these points into perspective and asked our DRs what is it like to be a doctoral researcher at a Helmholtz Center. Below, our survey team will tell you some of the key results from the survey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sY_L269sST4"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/images/LOGO_Blue2.png" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On July 13, the Helmholtz Juniors (you may know as HeJus) conducted their meeting in Berlin, which lasted for two days. More than 30 Juniors came from Helmholtz Centers all over Germany to join the Midterm Meeting taking place at the Helmholtz Association’s Headquarters (HGF) in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For weeks before the meeting, the Juniors were preparing the agenda and gathering information across all centers and the HeJus working groups on the working conditions of PhD students and also the major problems that the students at each center are facing. The agenda of the Midterm Meeting included discussions on the PhD contract model that HeJus Working Conditions group has been working on, and a session by &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.southampton.ac.uk/oes/postgraduate/research_students/km1g14.page" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Kyle Mayers&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Southampton on the British doctoral system. The agenda also included the ongoing preparations for the soon coming Helmholtz PhD conference “&lt;a class="link" href="https://indico.scc.kit.edu/indico/event/229/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;NextGen@Helmholtz&lt;/a&gt;” taking place this September at HZI in Braunschweig. The HeJus met up with the new members joining this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank you for following our live updates via &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and for your comments. Stay tuned for more details on the meeting&amp;rsquo;s recommendations!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Max-Planck society implements much-needed changes in PhD funding</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/max-planck-society-implements-much-needed-changes-in-phd-funding/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/max-planck-society-implements-much-needed-changes-in-phd-funding/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/max-planck-society-implements-much-needed-changes-in-phd-funding/images/800px-Euro_Banknotes.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Max-Planck society implements much-needed changes in PhD funding" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Stephan Körner, Julian Gethmann and Juliane Hafermann&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, we reported about the changes in the way PhD students are to be treated in the Helmholtz Association. As could be read in the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.zeit.de/2015/13/max-planck-institut-doktorand-forschung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;German news&lt;/a&gt; in March and April 2015, the Max Planck Society has meanwhile not been inactive: On March 23rd, the Max Planck Society published a &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.mpg.de/9067759/enhanced-funding-junior-scientists-max-planck-society" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; presenting a plan to spend “50 million Euro for junior scientists”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, one can split the attempts to improve the situation of PhD students and postdocs into two parts: give every doctoral student and every PostDoc a contract and improve the supervision by providing at least a second Professor as supervisor and mentor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;== The two-class society of stipend holders and contract holders==&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With more than 3400 stipend funded PhD students, the Max Planck Society is one of the biggest providers of PhD positions in Germany. Many PhD students come from abroad, and until now most of them have been provided with a stipend instead of a regular contract. But what is the problem with stipends? Although stipends offer benefits like more independence, they have some major disadvantages like lack of social securities, health and unemployment insurance, parental leave and pension, to name just a few. A more detailed description of the pros and cons of stipends can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To eliminate this funding-based difference between PhD students, the Max Planck Society will spend 50 million Euro per year to provide contracts instead of stipends to all of their doctoral students and postdocs. Furthermore, these contracts are granted for three years with an opportunity to extend for another year, so that students can focus on their work instead of worrying about follow-up funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the drawbacks of conventional staff contracts, however, is that PhD students also have to work on projects not related to their PhD topic (as it is e. g. still usual in engineering), such as giving lectures, supervising practical courses or performing routine tasks for their institute. Similar to the independence of these tasks granted by a stipend and unlike conventional contracts, these new PhD contracts are designed to ensure that you are not working on unrelated topics, but only on your own project. However, some drawbacks remain: there are exceptions to the no-stipend rule for guests working “on a particular project and for a limited time” who can still be funded by stipends without social security. These new guidelines do not affect any existing contracts or stipends and it is still unclear what the actual contracts encompass with regards to salary and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;== Supervision ==&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second big issue addressed is the situation of supervision of doctoral students and their perspectives after finishing the PhD. The Max Planck Society is aware of the situation that less than 10 % of PhDs stay in science. Therefore more than 90 % of the PhD students would benefit from courses and programs preparing them for jobs in industry or economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another more challenging approach for improving this situation is setting up contracts between the candidate, the supervising professor and another third person at a university. In the case of conflict between candidate and supervisor the third person mediates between the supervisor and the PhD student. The President of the Max Planck Society, Martin Statmann, hopes that each Professor supervising a student recognises and clearly communicates if a doctoral student is well suited for a career in research or if other branches seem to be more promising for the student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, this new development at the Max Planck Society is a big step in the right direction with still some minor flaws.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Association—improved conditions for PhD students</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/helmholtz-associationimproved-conditions-for-phd-students/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/helmholtz-associationimproved-conditions-for-phd-students/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/helmholtz-associationimproved-conditions-for-phd-students/images/phd-guidelines1.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Association—improved conditions for PhD students" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Juliane Hafermann, Julian Gethmann and Stephan Körner (Helmholtz Juniors Survey Group)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are moving in the scientific world: the working conditions of PhD students in two large German scientific societies, the Helmholtz Association and the Max Planck Society, will be improved dramatically. This week we will present recent developments at the Helmholtz Association. Stay tuned for more insights into the changes at the Max Planck society next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Helmholtz Association recently made huge progress in the way they treat PhD students. A working group chaired by Prof. Dirk Heinz and coordinated by Nina Löchte (who is responsible for the promotion of young and early-stage researchers and international networking) has prepared &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Doktoranden/epaper-PhD-Guidelines/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;guidelines for the completion of PhD projects&lt;/a&gt; within the Helmholtz Association. The &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/a&gt;, PhD representatives from every Helmholtz Centre in Germany, were also heard and involved in the process of writing these guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/helmholtz-associationimproved-conditions-for-phd-students/images/Karte_Helmholtz_Zentren_2010_72dpi.gif"
width="200"
height="253"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/helmholtz-associationimproved-conditions-for-phd-students/images/Karte_Helmholtz_Zentren_2010_72dpi_hu_988695aff3673251.gif 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/helmholtz-associationimproved-conditions-for-phd-students/images/Karte_Helmholtz_Zentren_2010_72dpi_hu_b497c20d074c04a3.gif 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Map of the Helmholtz Centres in Germany (By Froeder (Own work) , via Wikimedia Commons)"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="79"
data-flex-basis="189px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Germany’s largest scientific research organisation, the Helmholtz Association comprises 18 research centres working in six different fields: Energy, Earth and Environment, Health, Aeronautics, Space and Transport as well as Key Technologies plus Matter. A total of 36,000 staff work there, approximately 6,500 of them PhD students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These PhD students make a significant contribution to the research and the successes of the Helmholtz Association. Thus, the Helmholtz Association is interested in promoting and supporting them and their career with a talent management concept. 34 Research Schools and Graduate Schools have already been set up by the Helmholtz Association, offering a structured education and training for doctoral students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up the Graduate and Research Schools had been a first important step. Since then, further measures have been taken to improve the situation of PhD students within the Helmholtz Association. The Helmholtz PhD guidelines are an agreement on minimum standards that have to be met for the completion of PhD projects under optimal conditions. They strive to provide a wide range of training and development opportunities in order to prepare PhD students for their future careers in academia or industry as well as outside of research positions. Their aim is to create a common quality to the PhD training at all Helmholtz Centres, facilitate quality assurance and give guidance to both PhD students and their supervisors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guidelines make several recommendations for best practice during PhD training with the aim to turn these best practice examples into the minimal standards of PhD training within the Helmholtz Association. They endorse Research Schools and Graduate Schools, which provide a structured training and educational programme according to the needs of the individual PhD student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 9 out of the 18 Helmholtz centres award stipends, and according to the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.heju-survey.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;latest Helmholtz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Juniors Survey&lt;/a&gt;, 22 % of the survey participants are funded by a stipend. While stipends allow for more independence than conventional contracts do, they do not include health and pension insurance or other social securities. A more detailed comparison between stipends and contracts as well as all their benefits and drawbacks was published by the Helmholtz Juniors Working Conditions Group. The text is available in both German and English and can be found here:  &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/wp-content/uploads/sites/15/2015/05/20150429_Stipends_AHK.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Detailed information on stipends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to further improve the working conditions and the social security of PhD students in particular, the guidelines are an important step in the right direction as they advocate paid contracted positions including social security contributions. Furthermore, the guidelines state that the contract period should equal the expected duration of the PhD, with an optional extension period and additional funding until the dissertation is submitted in case the project cannot be completed within the allotted time frame. However, stipends as such are not ruled out, and awarding them as a source of funding for PhD students remains a possibility, leaving an obvious loophole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guidelines promote a system where the doctoral students do not solely depend on the goodwill of their supervisor. Instead, a committee of at least three scientists (one of them the primary supervisor) is to be informed about and consulted on the progress of the PhD project. This committee may furthermore give advice on career options and strategic questions during the PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PhD students are to be seen as “junior researchers undergoing preparation for their future careers through the process of completing a PhD”. The guidelines thus endorse support for career development, such as career advice and mentoring programmes for PhD students as well as career planning support after completion of the PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The formation of student bodies – such as PhD representatives at the individual centres or the Helmholtz Juniors as an association-wide PhD student body – is encouraged. That way, PhD students can get involved in future decisions affecting them and the support they receive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guidelines are certainly a great basis for the completion of PhD projects within the Helmholtz Association. However, there is one big drawback. So far, the guidelines are only best practice examples and recommendations. Every Helmholtz centre is technically free to choose which ones to implement and which ones to ignore. Furthermore, the situation of postdocs has not been addressed so far, which is another potential issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the Helmholtz centres have already set up conditions according to in accordance with parts of the guidelines, while still falling a short in other parts. In general, however, most PhD students enjoy good working conditions in the Helmholtz Association. The establishment of the PhD guidelines show that the necessity for changes has been recognised and that there is a willingness to improve the situation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Goodbye 2014, Hello 2015: Bring it on!</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/goodbye-2014-hello-2015-bring-it-on/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/goodbye-2014-hello-2015-bring-it-on/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/01/goodbye-2014-hello-2015-bring-it-on/images/HeJu2015.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Goodbye 2014, Hello 2015: Bring it on!" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The New Year 2015 is already a couple of days old. Let’s have a look back on the work of &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="Helmholtz-Juniors"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Juniors&lt;/a&gt; (HeJu) in 2014 and take a look ahead to what’s to expect for 2015. Yuan (see authors) compiled our current &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/wp-content/uploads/sites/15/2015/01/HeJu-Newsletter2014.pdf" title="HeJu-Newsletter 2014 (pdf)"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HeJu-Newsletter2014&lt;/a&gt; which gives you an overview about the work of 2014 and our contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From January 22 to 24, 2014 the HeJus were kindly hosted by the Helmholtz Centre Dresden-Rossendorf (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=0" title="HZDR"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZDR&lt;/a&gt;) in Dresden for their annual meeting. During that meeting the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" title="working groups"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;working groups&lt;/a&gt; presented their achievements of the previous term, and new goals where set for the next HeJu, namely us (most members are only active for one year, a list of currently active members you can find &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/current_helmholtz_juniors/" title="HeJu members"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The most important goals being set the realization of the Helmholtz PhD survey 2014 (survey group), the active participation in the formulation of an updated version of the official Helmholtz &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Doktoranden/Leitlinien_Doktorandenausbildung.pdf" title="PhD guidelines"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;doctoral training guidelines&lt;/a&gt; (working conditions group), the finalization of “the PhD booklet” (communication group) and coming up with a new concept for an interdisciplinary event for PhDs of the Helmholtz Association (HA) (events group). We also spoke with a Helmholtz official about financial support for our plans and the function and position of the HeJu within the HA. Additionally, we welcomed a representative of &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.phdnet.mpg.de" title="PhDnet"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;PhDnet&lt;/a&gt;, the PhD network of the Max Planck Society (MPG). Although being an official part of the MPG, they are known to be very critical towards their mother organization and fight for just working conditions and appropriate remuneration. They shared valuable information about their experience within the MPG and how they are organizing themselves. Vice versa Sripriya, one of our spokespersons last year, attended the annual meeting of PhDnet in Heidelberg later in 2014 and brought back interesting ideas for funding new events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also discussed current problems. For instance only 14 of the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/helmholtz_centres_networks/helmholtz_centres/" title="Helmholtz centres"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;18 Helmholtz centres&lt;/a&gt; were represented at the HeJu annual meeting, despite the centres agreeing to cover travel expenses for the meeting. Some representatives complained that the general will of students to engage for a representative function (meaning the DokTeams or PhD initiatives) at the individual centres was rather low among PhD students. It was also pointed out that there were difficulties in reaching all the PhD students working at one centre due to size, structural organization and the lack of networking possibilities. Other problems included the identification of the basic needs of PhD students of different subjects and at different centres (for instance: significantly lower salaries for PhDs in life science than for PhDs in engineering or similar subjects, not to mention PhDs in social science or the ones living on stipends).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From July 21 to 22 the HeJu met again at a mid-term meeting at the HA’s headquarters in Berlin thanks to the efforts of the events team who managed to get us comfortable in Berlin, and in touch with the headquarters for 2 days. This time 16 out of 18 centres were represented. A more detailed report about this event you can find &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/" title="HeJu Mid-Term Meeting 2014"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This gave us the possibility to check up on the progress of single projects and to rethink others. Just before the meeting the survey group put their questionnaire online and was able to show first figures (I hope you all took part!). The fully analysed results will soon follow (see below). Also a new working group was formed: the embodiment group. Inspired by the organization of PhDnet, its members were to evaluate if becoming an official body of the HA (including a fixed annual budget) was worth giving up our current independence. The working conditions group was actually able to leave their critical mark on the new doctoral training guidelines (to be released this year) and the communication group was invited to take a look behind the HA public relation department in order to increase HeJu&amp;rsquo;s visibility at the Helmholtz centres and beyond. As a result, we have this blog online since September 2014 and we hope you enjoy reading it. We will use it to keep you all updated about our work and also hope to get some discussions going about PhD life (or &lt;a class="link" href="http://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2014/11/life-after-phd/" title="Life after PhD"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;after life&lt;/a&gt;) in general. Feel free to leave your comments and ideas and have a look on our &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="Helmholtz-Juniors"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and our new &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors" title="HeJu Facebook"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;facebook page&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what’s to come in 2015? Big milestone ahead of course: the annual HeJu meeting at the Alfred Wegener Institute (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.awi.de" title="AWI"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;AWI&lt;/a&gt;) in Bremerhaven this week from January 14 to 16! There we will see how happy YOU are and at which centre you are happiest according to the results of the Helmholtz PhD survey. Information, each individual centre is also very interested in. We will present an online version of the PhD booklet (due to difficulties with the layout, a print version will only be available at a later time point but, we wanted to make sure that you can access this information asap). We hope that many of new and old PhD students in Germany will find it very useful. We will discuss our impact on the new Helmholtz doctoral training guidelines and the pros and cons of an official embodiment within the HA. We will see what concept the event group came up with and if we will again get support for an additional mid-term meeting. One of the more difficult topics is the question if PhD students should get stipends or contracts. There is a will of the HA to provide each PhD student with a contract rather than a stipend but, this is, of course, not yet reality. Given the tight financial situation for personnel money in science in general and at certain centres in particular, this will still be an issue in the future. An issue that probably has to be discussed with Otmar Wiestler, now head of the German Cancer Research Centre (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.dkfz.de" title="DKFZ"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;DKFZ&lt;/a&gt;), who will replace Jürgen Mlynek after 10 years as HA&amp;rsquo;s new president in September this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very important point will be the handing over of our work to the ones of you that will take over our tasks. Due to the short HeJu terms, a thorough transfer of information is crucial for an efficient continuation. Thus, let’s look forward to what the next HeJu generation will have in store for us. I will surely keep checking up on the news here. Good luck! :)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/MeetingProfM.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the end of July the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="HeJus"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Juniors&lt;/a&gt; (or more informally “HeJu”) got together for their mid-term meeting at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/" title="Helmholtz Association"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Association&lt;/a&gt;’s head office in Berlin. It was the second time we met this year after our first meeting at the Helmholtz Center Dresden-Rossendorf (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=139" title="HZDR"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZDR&lt;/a&gt;) in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is useful to mention here that the HeJu’s are not an official body of the Helmholtz Association, but a diverse group of volunteering PhD students who are committed to improve PhD working conditions and connect PhDs within the Helmholtz Association as well as within Germany (look at this &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/helmholtz_centres_networks/helmholtz_centres/" title="Helmholtz Centers"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; to see where we are located). This includes a cacophony of emails, phone calls, doodle lists, literature research and skype conferences. And all that we are trying to manage on the side to our own demanding PhD projects, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_318452cf8586dd02.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_5c0d26a0a1eaf992.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Members of the communication group are discussing content and style of the new HeJu Blog. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I was really looking forward to the meeting as we had set ambitious goals back in January and our predecessors had informed us that it might be difficult to keep up the motivation for our projects throughout the entire year. Thus, we decided to get together again already after half a year to renew our HeJu energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there we were: One and a half days full of reports, heated discussions, brainstorming and coffee overflow. First of all our spokespersons Nicholas and Sripriya and our four &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" title="Working Groups"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;working groups&lt;/a&gt; presented the progress so far. The main achievements have been the active participation in an update of the Helmholtz Association’s official PhD guidelines (which virtually has some effect on all Helmholtz PhD students), the finishing of our “Helmholtz PhD booklet” (we will keep you posted about this!) and the launch of this year’s &lt;a class="link" href="http://heju-survey.de" title="HeJu Survey"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;PhD survey&lt;/a&gt; (where every PhD student under Helmholtz can actually help to improve the conditions, hopefully you all took part. But, don’t worry if not, it’s still possible until Sep 19th!!! Go for it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_bc838b8887356475.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_a10fb63526318854.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Our events group organized the mid-term meeting and currently develops concepts for future PhD events. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our “events” group who was busy organizing this meeting we’ve been in close contact with officials of the Helmholtz Association and the direct feedback was helping a lot to shape common goals and to identify certain (im)possibilities. For instance, what financial support can we expect and what are the advantages and disadvantages of becoming an official body of the Helmholtz Association? A topic so fundamental, that the formation of a new working group was required to evaluate its pros and cons. But, a special treat for us was the visit of Prof. Dr. Jürgen Mlynek, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/president/" title="HA president"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;president&lt;/a&gt; of the Helmholtz Association, who took some time to welcome us personally in the headquarter and also stayed for a quick Q&amp;amp;A session (see header). How much closer can you get as a PhD student to the very head of your research organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_abed3c62ea1a0cea.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_b731d6a0c9399ad.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The newly established embodiment group will evaluate how to position the HeJu’s within the Helmholtz Association in the future. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During several sessions the individual working groups discussed and developed new ideas and eventually set the goals for the rest of the term. Furthermore, we were lucky to talk with the public relations officials, who gave us vital support on our visibility and communication structure as well as an insight into their day-to-day work. A result of which we have this brand new Blog you happened to be reading right now and the new &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors?fref=ts" title="HeJu FB"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HeJu’s logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is left to do for this year? Of course, the discussion on the PhD guidelines is not over yet and will go on. One goal, for example, is to increase contract positions for PhDs in relation to scholarships. The “survey” group will have a busy time analyzing the survey results and wrapping that up until January next year, when the HeJu’s meet again at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.awi.de/en/home/" title="AWI"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Alfred Wegener Institute&lt;/a&gt; in Bremerhaven. The PhD booklet will be published and available for everyone who’s interested (some interviews with the people involved will be up as well). We are also planning a special event where PhD students can connect and get information on career options and this Blog will be filled with more articles about our work as HeJu’s and topics about PhD life in general. Feel free to comment and ask questions below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715.jpg"
width="1000"
height="715"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_ba63b2c24e57ba16.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_62e4c2da3df96f65.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="As you might already have figured out, all that talking and discussing made our heads dizzy. We tried to counteract that feeling over a few drinks at Berlin’s open air summer nightlife locations. During which we discussed if the competition for Germany’s sexiest scientist award would be an appropriate HeJu-event to organize. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="139"
data-flex-basis="335px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>