<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hejus on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/hejus/</link><description>Recent content in Hejus on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/hejus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Check out the interview (1/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you the motivation and execution of our 2019 HeJu survey</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-1/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-the-motivation-and-execution-of-our-2019-heju-survey/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-1/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-the-motivation-and-execution-of-our-2019-heju-survey/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/11/check-out-the-interview-1/5-here-our-heju-survey-team-explains-you-the-motivation-and-execution-of-our-2019-heju-survey/images/Picture1.png" alt="Featured image of post Check out the interview (1/5) here! Our HeJu survey team explains you the motivation and execution of our 2019 HeJu survey" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being a doctoral researcher (DR) can sometimes lead us to a &amp;ldquo;solitary&amp;rdquo; journey. For instance, even within the same discipline, the researches we do still need certain extent of novelty so that many of us might never find some one doing exactly the same thing and have an in-depth chat about our passions. On the other hand, being doctoral researchers can also bring us a solidary benefit. We are that many (even within the Helmholtz society, there are currently about 8,500 DRs) and the greater challenges (beyond our specific research topic) are so similar for all of us (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03459-7%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03459-7)&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, staying connected with our peer DRs through networks as well as showing the representative status quo of our DR community is crucial to improve our living/working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is an example we have done as Helmholtz Juniors (HeJu) for showing our representative status quo of our DRs. We conduct a Helmholtz-wide PhD survey every two years and publish the results. We also communicate with the administrative units at each center by our local HeJu representatives and try to promote the living/working conditions for our DRs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our newest survey report is here: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/06_jobs_talente/Helmholtz-Juniors/Survey_Report2019_update.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And below is the interview with our survey team to explain you our motivation and execution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-wrapper"&gt;
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CqtTU_E4z40"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>1st NextGen meeting is coming soon</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/09/1st-nextgen-meeting-is-coming-soon/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/09/1st-nextgen-meeting-is-coming-soon/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/09/1st-nextgen-meeting-is-coming-soon/images/Logo_NextGen_4c_kl.png" alt="Featured image of post 1st NextGen meeting is coming soon" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;28th of September is approaching fast and it is going to be the first PhD retreat of all the Helmholtz institutes, organised by the Helmholtz Juniors (&lt;a class="link" href="https://indico.scc.kit.edu/indico/event/229/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to web page). Three days in Braunschweig for a multidisciplinary meeting that will involve 127 Doctoral Researchers and guests. Prof. Wiesler, President of the Helmholtz association, who believes on the importance of promoting the connection between Helmholtz institutes, will join for the expert panel talks, targeting the “Publish or Perish” philosophy in academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3 days will give the researcher the possibility to network and learn about other institutes and peers research, present their work, as well as meet with Alumni to discuss future opportunities after the PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the slogan says, this is a conference organised by PhDs for PhDs and it has as main focus bringing together experts in different disciplines to foster ideas and discussions outside their field. The world is moving to a multidisciplinary approach everyday more, and the Helmholtz institutes offer a variety of expertise that could collaborate together. In this direction goes the challenge of the multidisciplinary workshop that will see different teams compete to plan the best way to colonize Mars - future is never too far! Additionally, science slam will offer an opportunity to practice communication skills, also in an unconventional way - dancing, acting, talking, everything is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as Helmholtz Juniors, are excited for this great opportunity and grateful for the immense work the event group put to make these 3 days unforgettable for all the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you will like it and it will become the event the doctoral research will look forward in all the Helmholtz centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/07/helmholtz-juniors-midterm-meeting-2016-phd-contracts-and-british-doctoral-system-were-among-the-highlights/images/LOGO_Blue2.png" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors Midterm Meeting 2016: PhD contracts and British doctoral system were among the highlights" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;On July 13, the Helmholtz Juniors (you may know as HeJus) conducted their meeting in Berlin, which lasted for two days. More than 30 Juniors came from Helmholtz Centers all over Germany to join the Midterm Meeting taking place at the Helmholtz Association’s Headquarters (HGF) in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For weeks before the meeting, the Juniors were preparing the agenda and gathering information across all centers and the HeJus working groups on the working conditions of PhD students and also the major problems that the students at each center are facing. The agenda of the Midterm Meeting included discussions on the PhD contract model that HeJus Working Conditions group has been working on, and a session by &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.southampton.ac.uk/oes/postgraduate/research_students/km1g14.page" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Kyle Mayers&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Southampton on the British doctoral system. The agenda also included the ongoing preparations for the soon coming Helmholtz PhD conference “&lt;a class="link" href="https://indico.scc.kit.edu/indico/event/229/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;NextGen@Helmholtz&lt;/a&gt;” taking place this September at HZI in Braunschweig. The HeJus met up with the new members joining this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank you for following our live updates via &lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/HelmholtzJrs" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; and for your comments. Stay tuned for more details on the meeting&amp;rsquo;s recommendations!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/MeetingProfM.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the end of July the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="HeJus"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Juniors&lt;/a&gt; (or more informally “HeJu”) got together for their mid-term meeting at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/" title="Helmholtz Association"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Association&lt;/a&gt;’s head office in Berlin. It was the second time we met this year after our first meeting at the Helmholtz Center Dresden-Rossendorf (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=139" title="HZDR"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZDR&lt;/a&gt;) in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is useful to mention here that the HeJu’s are not an official body of the Helmholtz Association, but a diverse group of volunteering PhD students who are committed to improve PhD working conditions and connect PhDs within the Helmholtz Association as well as within Germany (look at this &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/helmholtz_centres_networks/helmholtz_centres/" title="Helmholtz Centers"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; to see where we are located). This includes a cacophony of emails, phone calls, doodle lists, literature research and skype conferences. And all that we are trying to manage on the side to our own demanding PhD projects, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_318452cf8586dd02.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_5c0d26a0a1eaf992.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Members of the communication group are discussing content and style of the new HeJu Blog. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I was really looking forward to the meeting as we had set ambitious goals back in January and our predecessors had informed us that it might be difficult to keep up the motivation for our projects throughout the entire year. Thus, we decided to get together again already after half a year to renew our HeJu energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there we were: One and a half days full of reports, heated discussions, brainstorming and coffee overflow. First of all our spokespersons Nicholas and Sripriya and our four &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" title="Working Groups"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;working groups&lt;/a&gt; presented the progress so far. The main achievements have been the active participation in an update of the Helmholtz Association’s official PhD guidelines (which virtually has some effect on all Helmholtz PhD students), the finishing of our “Helmholtz PhD booklet” (we will keep you posted about this!) and the launch of this year’s &lt;a class="link" href="http://heju-survey.de" title="HeJu Survey"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;PhD survey&lt;/a&gt; (where every PhD student under Helmholtz can actually help to improve the conditions, hopefully you all took part. But, don’t worry if not, it’s still possible until Sep 19th!!! Go for it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_bc838b8887356475.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_a10fb63526318854.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Our events group organized the mid-term meeting and currently develops concepts for future PhD events. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our “events” group who was busy organizing this meeting we’ve been in close contact with officials of the Helmholtz Association and the direct feedback was helping a lot to shape common goals and to identify certain (im)possibilities. For instance, what financial support can we expect and what are the advantages and disadvantages of becoming an official body of the Helmholtz Association? A topic so fundamental, that the formation of a new working group was required to evaluate its pros and cons. But, a special treat for us was the visit of Prof. Dr. Jürgen Mlynek, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/president/" title="HA president"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;president&lt;/a&gt; of the Helmholtz Association, who took some time to welcome us personally in the headquarter and also stayed for a quick Q&amp;amp;A session (see header). How much closer can you get as a PhD student to the very head of your research organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_abed3c62ea1a0cea.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_b731d6a0c9399ad.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The newly established embodiment group will evaluate how to position the HeJu’s within the Helmholtz Association in the future. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During several sessions the individual working groups discussed and developed new ideas and eventually set the goals for the rest of the term. Furthermore, we were lucky to talk with the public relations officials, who gave us vital support on our visibility and communication structure as well as an insight into their day-to-day work. A result of which we have this brand new Blog you happened to be reading right now and the new &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors?fref=ts" title="HeJu FB"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HeJu’s logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is left to do for this year? Of course, the discussion on the PhD guidelines is not over yet and will go on. One goal, for example, is to increase contract positions for PhDs in relation to scholarships. The “survey” group will have a busy time analyzing the survey results and wrapping that up until January next year, when the HeJu’s meet again at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.awi.de/en/home/" title="AWI"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Alfred Wegener Institute&lt;/a&gt; in Bremerhaven. The PhD booklet will be published and available for everyone who’s interested (some interviews with the people involved will be up as well). We are also planning a special event where PhD students can connect and get information on career options and this Blog will be filled with more articles about our work as HeJu’s and topics about PhD life in general. Feel free to comment and ask questions below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715.jpg"
width="1000"
height="715"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_ba63b2c24e57ba16.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_62e4c2da3df96f65.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="As you might already have figured out, all that talking and discussing made our heads dizzy. We tried to counteract that feeling over a few drinks at Berlin’s open air summer nightlife locations. During which we discussed if the competition for Germany’s sexiest scientist award would be an appropriate HeJu-event to organize. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="139"
data-flex-basis="335px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>