<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Statements on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/statements/</link><description>Recent content in Statements on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/categories/statements/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Nachhaltige Spitzenforschung durch faire Arbeitsbedingungen</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/07/nachhaltige-spitzenforschung-durch-faire-arbeitsbedingungen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/07/nachhaltige-spitzenforschung-durch-faire-arbeitsbedingungen/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/07/nachhaltige-spitzenforschung-durch-faire-arbeitsbedingungen/images/Blog-banner.png" alt="Featured image of post Nachhaltige Spitzenforschung durch faire Arbeitsbedingungen" /&gt;&lt;h3 id="sustainable-cutting-edge-research-through-fair-working-conditions-the-necessity-of-transparent-collective-agreements-for-doctoral-researchers-in-the-helmholtz-association"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustainable Cutting-Edge Research through Fair Working Conditions: The&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Necessity of Transparent Collective Agreements for Doctoral Researchers in the Helmholtz Association&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recruiting top national and international talent is a major challenge in the highly competitive field of academic research and is of crucial importance to the Helmholtz Association of German Research Centres (HGF). To succeed in the race for scientific progress, the HGF must offer attractive and reliable working conditions for its early-career researchers. In practice, however, individual contracts are predominantly concluded between the respective Helmholtz Centers and doctoral researchers, which reduces both the transparency of contract terms and the equal opportunity goals pursued by the HGF. As the voice of doctoral researchers within the HGF, the Helmholtz Juniors advocate for integrating all doctoral researchers employed at Helmholtz Centers into the collective agreement for the public sector (TVöD), pay grade E13. This is the only way to ensure fair and transparent working conditions and attract top-tier talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following outlines the advantages of collective agreements over individual contracts, often referred to as funding agreements. In contrast, scholarships typically fail to provide the necessary social security and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-create-transparency"&gt;Collective Agreements Create Transparency
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Science, as an international field of work, requires regulations that are transparent and understandable in an international context1. In a statement on the amendment of the Act on Temporary Scientific Contracts (WissZeitVG), the Alliance of Science Organisations in Germany warned against the risk of a confusing diversity of regulations and, in the worst case, disparities between institutions2. The Max Planck Society, for example, offers at least standardized (funding) contracts, whereas the HGF features a remarkable diversity of contracts for doctoral researchers. The most common type of contract in the HGF is individual, non-tariff agreements with durations of two to four years and compensation ranging from 55% to 100% of a full-time position. Only about a third of the centers apply the TVöD on an individual basis. Despite having an application agreement with the United Services Union (ver.di), two Helmholtz Centers effectively exclude doctoral researchers from the collective agreement by invoking § 1 para. 2 letter s of the TVöD. Two other centers are affiliated with universities due to their historical development and therefore apply the collective agreement for the public service of the federal states (TV-L), which uses a different pay scale. This inconsistent and arbitrary patchwork of rules not only prevents transparency but also creates inequalities among doctoral researchers within the HGF. This undermines equal opportunity and makes working conditions difficult to understand from an international perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-ensure-equal-opportunity"&gt;Collective Agreements Ensure Equal Opportunity
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improving equal opportunity is a central priority in the HGF - this principle is firmly anchored in the HGF&amp;rsquo;s mission and is an integral part of its talent management3. Through their uniformity, collective agreements are an important tool that can significantly promote equal opportunity across the HGF. Collective agreements establish a standardized minimum framework that is regularly negotiated publicly and applies to all doctoral researchers. They ensure standardized regulations for working hours and vacation, recognize professional experience in compensation, and provide social security through additional benefits such as occupational pension schemes. In contrast, individual contracts can vary significantly in content and are subject to the unilateral stipulations of funding bodies, such as the Federal Ministry for Research, Technology and Space (BMFTR), formerly the Federal Ministry for Education and Research (BMBF), which define only maximum standards - allowing individual institutes to make downward deviations at their discretion. This opens the door to potential misuse and disadvantages for individual doctoral researchers. With collective bargaining, any changes to the agreement are automatically applied to all employment contracts. In contrast, individual contracts only reflect new rules in newly signed agreements. Thus, collective agreements ensure full transparency and lay the foundation for equal opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-increase-attractiveness-and-satisfaction"&gt;Collective Agreements Increase Attractiveness and Satisfaction
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sustainable and fair working conditions are not only key to long-term viability but also decisive for the lasting attractiveness and success of research institutions in an increasingly competitive academic landscape - a principle the Helmholtz Association already established in its 2016 sustainability management guidelines (LeNa). These guidelines emphasized the importance of developing new career paths and avoiding precarious employment, particularly for early-career researchers&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;4&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Competitive working conditions are the basis for attracting and retaining talented young scientists from both national and international backgrounds5,6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2020 study found that good working conditions and career prospects are key drivers of innovation in academic research7. Establishing good working conditions has twofold benefits: on the one hand, secure employment leads to higher satisfaction and productivity&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn4" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;8&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftn4" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;; on the other hand, it enhances the employer’s appeal to international top talent. Job satisfaction is therefore a critical factor in the attractiveness of the public science sector. By introducing transparent, uniform contracts based on binding institutional application of the TVöD for doctoral researchers, the HGF can offer its early-career researchers sustainable, fair, and favorable working conditions - ensuring the retention of young talent amid a shortage of skilled workers in the public research sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="collective-agreements-reduce-bureaucracy"&gt;Collective Agreements Reduce Bureaucracy
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2023 inflation compensation payment demonstrated that the diversity of contract types results in increased administrative workload and uncertainty among doctoral researchers. Introducing the collective agreement for all doctoral researchers would simplify administrative processes and create independence from the directives of funding bodies such as the BMFTR, since collective bargaining law overrides ministerial guidelines and authorizations. This benefits both researchers and administrative staff, fosters a coherent and efficient organizational structure, enhances transparency, and strengthens the Helmholtz Centers&amp;rsquo; appeal as employers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we emphasize that the binding institutional application of the TVöD without exception for all doctoral researchers at all Helmholtz Centers is a necessary measure. It aligns with the interests of the HGF by increasing its competitiveness in recruiting national and international talent, ensuring high satisfaction and productivity among researchers, promoting equal opportunity, and simplifying administrative processes. By supporting this initiative, the HGF can further strengthen its position as a leading actor in research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Helmholtz Juniors represent around 8,000 doctoral researchers within the Helmholtz Association. They advocate for the introduction of collective agreements for doctoral researchers across the entire Helmholtz Association of German Research Centres. This position was unanimously adopted at the Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting in 2024.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref1" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;1 - &lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref1" &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Helmholtz-Promotionsleitlinien (2019), online unter:           &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/upload_Karriere/190520_Helmholtz_Promotionsleitlinien_DE.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/upload_Karriere/190520_Helmholtz_Promotionsleitlinien_DE.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 - Allianz der Wissenschaftsorganisationen, Stellungnahme 27. März 2023: Für attraktive wissenschaftliche Karrieren in Deutschland,         online unter: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/200230616_Allianz-Kommentierung_Referentenentwurf-WissZeitVG_Wissenschaftskarrieren-ermoeglichen_fin-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Wissenschaftskarrieren ermöglichen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/200230616_Allianz-Kommentierung_Referentenentwurf-WissZeitVG_Wissenschaftskarrieren-ermoeglichen_fin-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;–&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.allianz-der-wissenschaftsorganisationen.de/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/200230616_Allianz-Kommentierung_Referentenentwurf-WissZeitVG_Wissenschaftskarrieren-ermoeglichen_fin-1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Kommentierung der Allianz der Wissenschaftsorganisationen zum WissZeitVG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 - Helmholtz Homepage, online unter: &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;www.helmholtz.de/ueber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;uns/wer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;wir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;sind/zahlen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;und&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;fakten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/ueber-uns/wer-wir-sind/zahlen-und-fakten-neu/talentfoerderung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;neu/talentfoerderung,&lt;/a&gt; Stand 2024&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;4 -&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref2" &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Ferretti, J. et al.: LeNa-Handreichung. Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement in außeruniversitären Forschungsorganisationen, 2016, online unter: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/LeNa-Leitfaden_Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement_2016.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/fileadmin/user_upload/LeNa-Leitfaden_Nachhaltigkeitsmanagement_2016.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5 - Barcan, R. (2018). Paying dearly for privilege: conceptions, experiences and temporalities of vocation in academic life. &lt;em&gt;Pedagogy,&lt;/em&gt;        &lt;em&gt;Culture &amp;amp; Society,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;26&lt;/em&gt;, 105-121. &lt;a class="link" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14681366.2017.1358207" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/14681366.2017.1358207&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6 - Reymert, I., Vabø, A., Borlaug, S.B. &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (2023). Barriers to attracting the best researchers: perceptions of academics in economics       and physics in three European countries. &lt;em&gt;High Educ&lt;/em&gt; 86, 1173–1193 (2023). &lt;a class="link" href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10734-022-00967-w" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10734-022-00967-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref3" &gt;&lt;/a&gt;7 -&lt;a class="link" href="#_ftnref3" &gt;&lt;/a&gt; Castellacci, F., &amp;amp; Viñas-Bardolet, C. (2020). Permanent contracts and job satisfaction in academia: evidence from European      countries. Studies in Higher Education, 46(9), 1866–1880. &lt;a class="link" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03075079.2019.1711041" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/03075079.2019.1711041&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 - Bryson, Alex and Forth, John and Stokes, Lucy, Does Worker Wellbeing Affect Workplace Performance? IZA Discussion Paper No. 9096, Available at SSRN: &lt;a class="link" href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=2655044" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://ssrn.com/abstract=2655044&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="link" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2655044" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2655044&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to communicate your problems</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/03/how-to-communicate-your-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/03/how-to-communicate-your-problems/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2025/03/how-to-communicate-your-problems/images/Blog-banner.png" alt="Featured image of post How to communicate your problems" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Author: Anonymous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open communication is key for a good working environment, effective collaboration, and a healthy relationship with your co-workers and supervisors. The ability to communicate well is crucial for working efficiently and successfully- especially during a doctorate. It is well known that a doctorate comes with a multitude of challenges unrelated to the actual research itself. Young researchers often face problems that are not only related to completely neutral working topics but are also on a personal level, which brings emotions into the mix. This includes problems with co-workers and quite often with the supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being emotionally involved makes it more challenging to communicate issues effectively and in a constructive manner. The real problem then is often not the actual problem, but rather the stimulated emotions. To make matters worse, communicating feelings at work is still sometimes perceived as unprofessional, weak, and inappropriate when precisely the opposite is true. Good communication is essential for maintaining not only a healthy working environment, but also good mental health and a free mind. In addition, learning how to communicate effectively leads to both personal and interpersonal growth. So, &lt;strong&gt;what IS the best way to communicate your problems and how it makes you feel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is no one single solution for all problems, here are some general pointers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before reacting impulsively with strong emotions, take a deep breath and try to distance yourself from the situation. Practice some self-awareness. What is it that you are feeling? Understand your own emotions, so you can express yourself more clearly. Depending on the situation, it might be helpful to talk to a trusted friend or colleague about the circumstances. Maybe write down what the problem is and how it makes you feel. Where did this problem originate, and do you have a solution you could propose? Do you think you can solve the problem by yourself? If not, don’t hesitate to tackle the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When addressing problems, remember: the time and place matter. Choose a moment when both parties are receptive. Talk somewhere where you will not be interrupted or disturbed. Both parties should take the time needed to discuss with no time limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When communicating your problems, try to be as clear and specific as possible. Explain your problems and interests and if possible, give concrete examples. This helps the other party understand the issue and makes the issue tangible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People tend to quickly feel attacked, therefore when talking about the problem, use “I-statements”. Employ phrases such as “This gives me the feeling&amp;hellip;” or “This gives me the impression&amp;hellip;” and avoid direct confrontations like “You are&amp;hellip;” or “You always do XYZ&amp;hellip;”. Criticism in any situation should remain constructive. By staying with your emotions, it shifts the focus to your feelings and promotes empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to express how a problem is affecting &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, how it makes &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; feel. This more constructive than blaming or attacking the other person directly, which should be avoided. Direct criticism of a person can hurt the other party, incite retaliation, and create even more problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different points of view for every problem. The main goal is for all parties to understand each others’ points of view. This can help deescalate the situation and hopefully lead to a resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to the other party and allow them to answer without interruption. Keep in mind that their feelings are also valid. Try to understand their point of view and listen to their interests. If the situation becomes emotional, make sure to stay calm and respectful to foster a more positive outcome. Be open to apologizing when needed or appropriate. Maybe the other party did react out of emotions as well and both of you can approach each other. Try to stay in the present with a focus on the future. Do not be too hung up on the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are often dependencies in a working environment which you cannot easily dissolve or also do not intend to. That is why it is important to seek for a solution together which is suitable for all parties. Try to find areas of agreement upon which you can build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use expressions such as: “I feel like we are stuck, and I understand that the underlying reasons could be this and this. I would need a more supportive collaboration, and therefore I would appreciate X and Y. Of course, I want to support you on the same level. What would you need? How can we improve the situation?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After communicating your problem, take some time and reflect on the situation and on what was discussed. Keep up the communication to ensure progress in resolving the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel that the communication barrier is too high, involving a mediator can be a good idea. This can be a supervisor, but also an ombudsperson. Companies and institutes do often have persons specially trained in helping handle and resolve such situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in some working environments, communicating your problems as a female comes with even more challenges such as being perceived as weak, and when speaking up, pushy. Here, it is important to not let yourself be silenced. If you face unjust criticism, stay consistent, stay strong. Such reactions say more about them and their inability to interface with strong women and less about you. In such situations it might be helpful to speak up and clearly reject such statements. Do not tolerate sexism at any point. Females communicating problems in a constructive, calm manner should not be subject to being called “tough” and “pushy” and being told to get out of their “victim-hood”. This is a failure in communication by the other party, and we suggest asking for a mediator or talking to a supervisor. Do not, however, let it stop you from communicating your problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, communication styles differ from culture to culture. While Germans tend to have a very direct way of communication, this is different in other cultures. The German way of communication can be perceived as impolite or offensive. However, in some cultures, silence is a strong form of communication, which can be missed if one is unaware of such culture-specific cues. These cultural differences should always be kept in mind and considered, especially in our very international work environment.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Quo vadis academic, when the contract expires?</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2024/02/quo-vadis-academic-when-the-contract-expires/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2024/02/quo-vadis-academic-when-the-contract-expires/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2024/02/quo-vadis-academic-when-the-contract-expires/images/Joingt-Statment-WissZeitVG-170323-5.png" alt="Featured image of post Quo vadis academic, when the contract expires?" /&gt;&lt;h4 id="wisszeitvg-commentary"&gt;WissZeitVG Commentary
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;h5 id="a-guest-entry-by-johannes-krämer-heju-spokesperson-2023"&gt;&lt;em&gt;a guest entry by Johannes Krämer (HeJu Spokesperson 2023)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the state of freedom of science and academia today? The idea of academic freedom dates back long ago, and in short, ascertains that academics can conduct and communicate their research or teach without the fear of repression, job loss, or imprisonment. However, job security and career perspectives have been found to be among the biggest drawbacks of scientific careers in Germany [1]. One important tool to regulate this within the German academic system is the &lt;em&gt;Act on Fixed Term Employment Contracts in Academia&lt;/em&gt; (WissenschaftsZeitVertragsGesetz - WissZeitVG) [2].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WissZeitVG regulates fixed term contracts. More precisely, it regulates the maximal duration one is allowed to be employed on a fixed term contract in academia. It does not regulate working hours, salaries, vacation days, etc. neither does it explicitly address working conditions, supervision of doctoral researchers, or project funding resources. It does not even regulate extensions, except defining an upper limit for the summed up contract time on fixed term contracts. So what&amp;rsquo;s all the fuss about if it&amp;rsquo;s “only about fixed-term contracts”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though the WissZeitVG mainly regulates maximum contract duration, this regulation causes far-reaching consequences for the academic environment. It impacts the structure of research institutions, where a professor and a handful of researchers reside in those limited permanent positions, whereas a large number of postdoctoral researchers, staff scientists, lecturers, and doctoral researchers – the ones, who are performing major parts of the scientific and higher educational work – are employed with fixed term contracts. And yes, for doctoral researchers, this is easily comprehensible, since they work towards a clearly defined qualification goal in order to graduate and then move on to a new chapter of their career. But for postdoctoral researchers, no such clear qualification exists, and they simply gain experience in their field of work, hoping to land one of those rare permanent positions. But it’s not just the structure of working groups, departments, or institutes, the funding system is also tailored to the current constraints given by the WissZeitVG. If these were now changed and all fixed-term contracts for postdoctoral researches were removed instantaneously, this would result in a collapse of the system. There are not enough permanent positions available nowadays and no additional funds to increase these numbers. The other extreme – allowing only unlimited fixed-term contracts in academia – would risk that highly skilled employees remain in uncertainty for their whole working life, always in fear of losing their job and either need to relocate far away from their homes or not finding new employment due to being overqualified. Aspects that can have a negative impact on their productivity and well-being. These and many more aspects need to be taken into account, when discussing the WissZeitVG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evaluation of the WissZeitVG, published in 2022, has shown the need of an amendment to prevent precarious working conditions in academia [3]. Details on the poor functions and precarious conditions in the current system can also be found in the 2021 National Report on Junior Scholars (BuWiN) [4]. Too many chain contracts, the majority of people on fixed-term contracts, and over 85 % leaving academia within 10 years after graduation of their doctorate. The constant fear of losing one’s job or not being able to get a subsequent contract. Not being able to plan one’s career in the long term without depending on fortunate circumstances. Sinking into work in order to perform best in the next evaluation, and putting in countless hours of unpaid overtime to do so. All this makes academia a precarious field of work. Seeing that many doctoral researches still have the ambition to pursue an academic career [5], is at odds with the number of positions available. However, it also shows that researchers are genuinely eager to contribute to science and thus to the benefit of society**.**&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WissZeitVG needs to give prospects for those who stay in academia, “permanency” on fixed-term contracts may not be the answer to that. Making an academic career more predictable may make it more attractive to those groups, which are currently underrepresented. Females, first-gen academics, and all of those who cannot take the risk to spend many years in precarious conditions or who do not have the financial protection to bridge the time between contracts. On the other hand, leaving academia in a shorter period of time after graduation can be beneficial to proceed with a career outside of academia and gain required experiences there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we were able to resolve all questions around the WissZeitVG in a blog post, the ongoing political process of the amendment of the act would not have been as tedious as it is. Finding solutions to problems arising in complex systems is not an easy task: and academia with its heterogeneity is a very complex system indeed. Here, we can only try to illustrate some aspects related to the topic, which might help to find a common ground for further discussions on the law itself. More detailed information on the position of HeJu and other doctoral researcher networks, as well as many other employee representations and unions who came together in a strong alliance can be found in our joint statement [6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how the new amendment of the WissZeitVG will look like, it can only set the direction for what the academic environment will look like in the future. Many more steps have to be taken. The funding scheme needs to be adjusted accordingly. If fixed-term contracts are allowed for shorter periods, we need more permanent positions, thus, more funding for these types of positions is needed. Since it is unlikely that the total amount of money available for academia will grow strongly as funding remains limited, we need to optimize the selection of people for permanent positions, and accompany them during their careers, starting when they are already students and doctoral researchers. Other options, like the utilization of the regular fixed-term contract act (Teilzeit- und Befristungsgesetz, TzB) for postdoctoral researchers may be taken into account, in particular when being equipped with exceptional conditions as in the case of young investigator group leaders or similar positions. We might even need to reconsider how “&lt;em&gt;permanent”&lt;/em&gt; permanent positions will be. A permanent contract in academia will no longer be understood as a contract for the entire working life. Changing jobs within academia, since permanent positions are no longer the rare win in the lottery, will become normal. Breaking the one-way job transitions from academia to industry - but (almost) never &lt;em&gt;vice versa -&lt;/em&gt; will lead to a more dynamic setting where people change jobs and contribute a broader range of skills. Academia will be benefiting if it adapts to the new rules. In times of skilled workers shortage, we cannot risk losing the best educated. And we need to provide attractive conditions for internationals to shift the brain drain into a brain gain, which will eventually benefit many more areas beside the academic field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, no solution will meet all demands of all stakeholders, but we should not be afraid of substantial changes, if we want to truly improve the working conditions in academia. We shouldn’t make ill-advised decisions, and every possible adjustment of the WissZeitVG opens even more questions, which might need to be answered. Politicians have taken serious efforts to find a solution, which meets the expectations of employers and employees alike. We hope that they will continue to discuss with representatives of doctoral researchers, and listen to their advice as well as to the consultation of other parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last point to keep in mind: The doctoral researchers, as well as Bachelor and Master students of today, are the first generation affected by the amendment of the WissZeitVG. They might be inexperienced in questions of funding schemes and contract details, but they know best how it feels to look into their own future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s create a bright future for those bright minds, so that their academic endeavors are free again and not overshadowed by the fear of the extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.humboldt-foundation.de/en/entdecken/magazin-humboldt-kosmos/whats-next/an-eldorado-for-research-and-bureaucracy" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Germany from the outside&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.gesetze-im-internet.de/wisszeitvg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Gesetz über befristete Arbeitsverträge in der Wissenschaft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bmbf.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/de/2022/abschlussbericht-evaluation-wisszeitvg.pdf?__blob=publicationFile&amp;amp;v=2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Evaluation des novellierten Wissenschaftszeitvertragsgesetzes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.buwin.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;2021 National Report on Junior Scholars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/en/career/careers-at-helmholtz/phd-candidates/helmholtz-juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;N²&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/en/career/careers-at-helmholtz/phd-candidates/helmholtz-juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;survey 2021 report for the Helmholtz Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;a class="link" href="https://blogs.helmholtz.de/hejus/2023/07/n%c2%b2-position-statement-on-the-draft-bill-to-amend-the-act-on-fixed-term-employment-contracts-in-academia-wisszeitvg-send-by-bmbf-on-14-06-2023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;N² position statement on the draft bill to amend the Act on Fixed Term Employment Contracts in Academia (WissZeitVG)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>