<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Phd on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/phd/</link><description>Recent content in Phd on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/phd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Mental Health Awareness - Part 1: Workload</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/Slide1.png" alt="Featured image of post Mental Health Awareness - Part 1: Workload" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Health Awareness&lt;/strong&gt; is a concern all year long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in some countries May is the Mental Health Awareness Month, in other its October. We want to use both!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For May we have something different prepared. The &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.universitaetsverlagwebler.de/_files/ugd/7bac3c_6974dfc41c054e3b94ff8590718fe819.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Mental Health Paper&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a class="link" href="https://de.linkedin.com/in/ivona-kafedjiska-227166ba?trk=public_post_share-update_actor-text&amp;amp;original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.linkedin.com%2F" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Ivona Kafedjiska&lt;/a&gt;, Lea Heckmann, Vanessa Pires, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pankhuri-s/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Pankhuri Saxena&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Jana Lasser made quite an impression amongst the community this year [1]. Our post summarizes the most important parts of each subtopic included in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1st part of the series: &lt;strong&gt;Workload&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/1-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/1-1000x1000_hu_653ac4e8948fec9e.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/1-1000x1000_hu_82b37b52f8af9b9e.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/2-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/2-1000x1000_hu_cda462b6e5bac00d.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/2-1000x1000_hu_d9dafed1ca6ce7f5.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/3-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/3-1000x1000_hu_f631a006fcbeb16a.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/3-1000x1000_hu_276b0325405f3dfc.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/4-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/4-1000x1000_hu_b62ca7b8467792d1.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/4-1000x1000_hu_d7d7a8389414fc54.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/5-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/5-1000x1000_hu_eb4e566ab2be71b5.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/5-1000x1000_hu_e84e9013db42d530.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/6-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/6-1000x1000_hu_704d11fa2282bd52.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/6-1000x1000_hu_eafc2606d503a8ff.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/7-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/7-1000x1000_hu_99404a57d515c340.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/7-1000x1000_hu_dc4fb770c4417bf8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/8-1000x1000.png"
width="1000"
height="1000"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/8-1000x1000_hu_7a988cce45722d55.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2022/05/mental-health-awareness-part-1-workload/images/8-1000x1000_hu_379b1a1b2b8c528a.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]    Kafedjiska, I., Heckmann, L., Pires, V., Saxena, P., &amp;amp; Lasser, J. (2022). The Mental Health Crisis among Doctoral Researchers – Findings and Best Practices. &lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift für Beratung und Studium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;17&lt;/em&gt;(1), 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images: Jakob Rauscher, Aniket Raje&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Possible Stressors and Signs of Stress</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors.png" alt="Featured image of post HeJu Mental Health Awareness Month (Oct 2020) – Possible Stressors and Signs of Stress" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stressors can be various, but for Doctoral Researchers, it mostly starts with a high workload and high expectations – which potentially activates a downwards spiral: This can lead to less time for hobbies (friends, sports etc.), which can be leading to sleeplessness and therefore tiredness and in the end potentially social isolation. But everyone deals with stress differently. Some seem pretty robust when it comes to stress – mainly because they´ve learned how to personally deal with stress. While some seem very prone to stress and react with severe psychological as well as physiological symptoms. In the end, nobody is immune to stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you been waking up in the middle of the night because you were thinking about a project you need to finish soon? Do you feel overrun because you can´t keep up with the project outline? Do you feel chased by deadline after deadline? Are you feeling tired a lot? Do you have twitching muscles, like your eyelids or fingers? Has your appetite changed? Have you gained or lost a lot of weight? Have you felt struggled to concentrate on work? If you answered yes to any of these questions, then you are probably stressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors.png"
width="907"
height="906"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors_hu_5c727616c1815ccc.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2020/10/heju-mental-health-awareness-month-oct-2020-possible-stressors-and-signs-of-stress/images/Stressors_hu_c25a5ead9faa8f3f.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People tend to overlook these early signs or do not take them seriously. We think, in a few days everything will be fine again. We think we need to function or otherwise we´re worthless. We think our whole future depends on this one talk we have to hold within the institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But often these signs last - and you slowly start getting used to them. But the stress itself &lt;strong&gt;is still there&lt;/strong&gt; and the signs of stress get worse. At some point, they might even lead to the burnout syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it is very useful to learn for yourself which signs of stress you are experiencing. Knowing your personal symptoms already helps to prevent further stress and prevent letting it slip and get worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, by increasing your knowledge in this topic you might be able to identify such signs in your colleagues who might be eager to have someone understand what they are going through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is no sign of weakness to admit that you are stressed and need a break!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, be honest with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A non-stressed you is way more productive than a completely stressed-out you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep that in mind!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mental Health Awareness Month post series is brought to you by Helmholtz Juniors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Pedro Ivo Silva Batista (DESY), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Michaela Löffler (UFZ), Nicolas Stoll (AWI), Fabian Wolf (GEOMAR), Younes Bouhadjar (FZJ), Stephanie Taylor (DZNE), Khwab Sanghvi (DKFZ), Lukas Kreis (GSI), Johannes Nelles (UFZ), Vasundhra Shaw (DESY) and Olya Oppenheim (MDC) for the text and Marlene Härtel (HZB), Martin Schrader (HZDR), Anna-Lena Amend (HMGU) and Xin You (UFZ) for the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow us and keep up2date with our work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.helmholtz.de/karriere_talente/wissenschaft/promovierende/helmholtz_juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://www.instagram.com/helmholtz.juniors/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;https://twitter.com/helmholtzjrs/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Max-Planck society implements much-needed changes in PhD funding</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/max-planck-society-implements-much-needed-changes-in-phd-funding/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/max-planck-society-implements-much-needed-changes-in-phd-funding/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/05/max-planck-society-implements-much-needed-changes-in-phd-funding/images/800px-Euro_Banknotes.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Max-Planck society implements much-needed changes in PhD funding" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Stephan Körner, Julian Gethmann and Juliane Hafermann&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, we reported about the changes in the way PhD students are to be treated in the Helmholtz Association. As could be read in the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.zeit.de/2015/13/max-planck-institut-doktorand-forschung" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;German news&lt;/a&gt; in March and April 2015, the Max Planck Society has meanwhile not been inactive: On March 23rd, the Max Planck Society published a &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.mpg.de/9067759/enhanced-funding-junior-scientists-max-planck-society" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt; presenting a plan to spend “50 million Euro for junior scientists”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, one can split the attempts to improve the situation of PhD students and postdocs into two parts: give every doctoral student and every PostDoc a contract and improve the supervision by providing at least a second Professor as supervisor and mentor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;== The two-class society of stipend holders and contract holders==&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With more than 3400 stipend funded PhD students, the Max Planck Society is one of the biggest providers of PhD positions in Germany. Many PhD students come from abroad, and until now most of them have been provided with a stipend instead of a regular contract. But what is the problem with stipends? Although stipends offer benefits like more independence, they have some major disadvantages like lack of social securities, health and unemployment insurance, parental leave and pension, to name just a few. A more detailed description of the pros and cons of stipends can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To eliminate this funding-based difference between PhD students, the Max Planck Society will spend 50 million Euro per year to provide contracts instead of stipends to all of their doctoral students and postdocs. Furthermore, these contracts are granted for three years with an opportunity to extend for another year, so that students can focus on their work instead of worrying about follow-up funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the drawbacks of conventional staff contracts, however, is that PhD students also have to work on projects not related to their PhD topic (as it is e. g. still usual in engineering), such as giving lectures, supervising practical courses or performing routine tasks for their institute. Similar to the independence of these tasks granted by a stipend and unlike conventional contracts, these new PhD contracts are designed to ensure that you are not working on unrelated topics, but only on your own project. However, some drawbacks remain: there are exceptions to the no-stipend rule for guests working “on a particular project and for a limited time” who can still be funded by stipends without social security. These new guidelines do not affect any existing contracts or stipends and it is still unclear what the actual contracts encompass with regards to salary and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;== Supervision ==&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second big issue addressed is the situation of supervision of doctoral students and their perspectives after finishing the PhD. The Max Planck Society is aware of the situation that less than 10 % of PhDs stay in science. Therefore more than 90 % of the PhD students would benefit from courses and programs preparing them for jobs in industry or economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another more challenging approach for improving this situation is setting up contracts between the candidate, the supervising professor and another third person at a university. In the case of conflict between candidate and supervisor the third person mediates between the supervisor and the PhD student. The President of the Max Planck Society, Martin Statmann, hopes that each Professor supervising a student recognises and clearly communicates if a doctoral student is well suited for a career in research or if other branches seem to be more promising for the student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, this new development at the Max Planck Society is a big step in the right direction with still some minor flaws.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The “Helmholtz community feeling”</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Hermann_von_Helmholtz_01-e1424100244809.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The “Helmholtz community feeling”" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Hermann_von_Helmholtz_01-209x300.jpg"
width="209"
height="300"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Hermann_von_Helmholtz_01-209x300_hu_df274e841c531aff.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Hermann_von_Helmholtz_01-209x300_hu_738cca89ec5b5b23.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Hermann von Helmholtz (Bild: gemeinfrei)"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="69"
data-flex-basis="167px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the sidelines of the Helmholtz Juniors Annual Meeting in January, an interesting idea came up: our work would be much easier if there was a strong sense of community – in other words, if we “felt more Helmholtz”. As the well-known blue-white Helmholtz logo can be found on the websites (just have a look at the top of this page), letter paper, business cards, etc. of each Centre, I wondered what this name actually represents and started looking for clues&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patron of the Helmholtz Association is &lt;strong&gt;Hermann von Helmholtz&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the leading natural scientists of the 19th century. He was interested in a wide range of scientific research and technological practice covering the fields of physics, medicine, mathematics and chemistry as well as psychology, philosophy and music. He was one of the last all-round academics not specialized in only one field. His inventions successfully linked theoretical approaches, experiments and practical applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born 1821 in Potsdam as Hermann Ludwig Ferdinand Helmholtz (the “von” came much later with his ennoblement), he was interested in the natural sciences ever since his early youth. As requested by his father and for financial reasons, he studied at the Berlin Military Academy and obtained his Doctor of Medicine at the age of 21. Over the years, he took several academic positions: associate professor of physiology at the Prussian University of Königsberg (1849, after being recommended by Alexander von Humboldt), professor of anatomy and physiology at the University of Bonn (1855), professor of physiology at the University of Heidelberg (1858) and finally, professor of physics at the University of Berlin (from 1871).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1887 the Physikalisch-Technische Reichsanstalt (PTR) was founded in Charlottenburg as the first non-university research centre worldwide and Helmholtz was not only one of the founders but also the first president. The PTR was kind of a forerunner for the present-day Helmholtz Association (and by the way, it still exists as the Physikalisch-Technische Bundesanstalt (PTB), Germany’s national metrology institute). Helmholtz was married twice and had three sons and two daughters. 1894 he died in Charlottenburg and was buried in a “grave of honour” at a cemetery in Berlin-Wannsee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/800px-Ehrengrab_Lindenstr_1_%28Zehld%29_Hermann_Helmholtz.jpg"
width="800"
height="569"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/800px-Ehrengrab_Lindenstr_1_%28Zehld%29_Hermann_Helmholtz_hu_8ca9e265288f966c.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/800px-Ehrengrab_Lindenstr_1_%28Zehld%29_Hermann_Helmholtz_hu_ca279b683b8f3d57.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Helmholtz’s grave of honour at Berlin-Wannsee [3]"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="140"
data-flex-basis="337px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research and Innovations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helmholtz made many outstanding contributions in a great range of scientific fields. As it would be impossible to mention them all in this blog entry, I focussed on several significant ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;physiology&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;psychology&lt;/strong&gt;, his research dealt with the mathematics of the eye and theories of vision, such as colour vision and the visual perception of space, as well as perception of sound and the sensation of tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His first contribution to &lt;strong&gt;physics&lt;/strong&gt; was a theoretical research on the conversation of energy for which he formulated a law. He also was the first scientist ever to measure the wavelengths of UV light and determine the capacity of a light microscope. His “three component theory of colour vision” which replaced the earlier six component model became especially relevant for colour television much later. In the field of &lt;strong&gt;acoustics&lt;/strong&gt;, he worked on the theory of air speed in open tubes and his research on &lt;strong&gt;hydrodynamics&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;electrodynamics&lt;/strong&gt; set new standards for the coming generations. A device still used nowadays is the &lt;strong&gt;Helmholtz coil&lt;/strong&gt;, which is able to produce a region of almost uniform magnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Helmholtz_coils-280x300.png"
width="280"
height="300"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Helmholtz_coils-280x300_hu_e76851b1c1e0884.png 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Helmholtz_coils-280x300_hu_809355002e7d5129.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Helmholtz Coils [4]"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="93"
data-flex-basis="224px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;mathematics&lt;/strong&gt;, he made a major impact on modern meteorology as he studied thunderstorms, cyclones, water waves and air waves. The mathematical formulation of the first theorem of thermodynamics also goes back to Helmholtz. The partial differential &lt;strong&gt;Helmholtz equation&lt;/strong&gt; is often used in physical studies of problems in both space and time domain and was named for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the field of &lt;strong&gt;optics&lt;/strong&gt;, he invented the &lt;strong&gt;ophthalmoscope&lt;/strong&gt; (in German “Augenspiegel”), an instrument to visualize the retina of the eye for the first time ever, which made him suddenly world-famous. Another instrument developed by him is the &lt;strong&gt;ophtalmometer&lt;/strong&gt;, which is used to measure the curvature of the surface of the cornea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Helmholtz was also interested in &lt;strong&gt;philosophy&lt;/strong&gt;. In this field, he developed theories about the philosophy of science and the link between the laws of nature and perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Statue_Unter_den_Linden_6_Mitte_Hermann_von_Helmholtz-194x300.jpg"
width="194"
height="300"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Statue_Unter_den_Linden_6_Mitte_Hermann_von_Helmholtz-194x300_hu_d738f42e980535d2.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2015/02/the-helmholtz-community-feeling/images/Statue_Unter_den_Linden_6_Mitte_Hermann_von_Helmholtz-194x300_hu_ca08c9aff7762140.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Helmholtz Statue in central Berlin [5]"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="64"
data-flex-basis="155px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that in mind, it is obvious why the six research fields of the Helmholtz Association cover the wide range of Energy, Earth and Environment, Health, Aeronautics, Space and Transport, Key Technologies and Matter. The Helmholtz Juniors come from all the different Helmholtz Centres and therefore represent this broad bandwidth. For a good sense of community and a successful teamwork in 2015, I hope very much that we will all feel “a bit more Helmholtz” and maybe this article helps a little bit on the way there&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about&lt;/a&gt;_us/history_of_the_helmholtz_association/hermann_von_helmholtz/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a class="link" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann&lt;/a&gt;_von_Helmholtz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] „Ehrengrab Lindenstr 1 (Zehld) Hermann Helmholtz“. Bild: OTFW, Berlin. Lizenz: &lt;a class="link" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/legalcode" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ehrengrab_Lindenstr_1_%5c%28Zehld%5c%29_Hermann_Helmholtz.jpg#mediaviewer/File:Ehrengrab_Lindenstr_1_%5c%28Zehld%5c%29_Hermann_Helmholtz.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;(zur Originaldatei)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] &amp;ldquo;Helmholtz coils&amp;rdquo; Bild: Ansgar Hellwig. Lizenz: &lt;a class="link" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/legalcode" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Helmholtz_coils.png#mediaviewer/File:Helmholtz_coils.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;(zur Originaldatei)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] „Statue Unter den Linden 6 (Mitte) Hermann von Helmholtz“. Bild: OTFW, Berlin. Lizenz: &lt;a class="link" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/legalcode" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="link" href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Statue_Unter_den_Linden_6_%5c%28Mitte%5c%29_Hermann_von_Helmholtz.jpg#mediaviewer/File:Statue_Unter_den_Linden_6_%5c%28Mitte%5c%29_Hermann_von_Helmholtz.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;(zur Originaldatei)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/MeetingProfM.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Helmholtz Juniors' Mid-Term Meeting 2014" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the end of July the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/working_at_helmholtz/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/" title="HeJus"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz-Juniors&lt;/a&gt; (or more informally “HeJu”) got together for their mid-term meeting at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/" title="Helmholtz Association"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Helmholtz Association&lt;/a&gt;’s head office in Berlin. It was the second time we met this year after our first meeting at the Helmholtz Center Dresden-Rossendorf (&lt;a class="link" href="http://www.hzdr.de/db/Cms?pNid=139" title="HZDR"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HZDR&lt;/a&gt;) in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is useful to mention here that the HeJu’s are not an official body of the Helmholtz Association, but a diverse group of volunteering PhD students who are committed to improve PhD working conditions and connect PhDs within the Helmholtz Association as well as within Germany (look at this &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/helmholtz_centres_networks/helmholtz_centres/" title="Helmholtz Centers"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; to see where we are located). This includes a cacophony of emails, phone calls, doodle lists, literature research and skype conferences. And all that we are trying to manage on the side to our own demanding PhD projects, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_318452cf8586dd02.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/Communications-300x199_hu_5c0d26a0a1eaf992.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Members of the communication group are discussing content and style of the new HeJu Blog. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I was really looking forward to the meeting as we had set ambitious goals back in January and our predecessors had informed us that it might be difficult to keep up the motivation for our projects throughout the entire year. Thus, we decided to get together again already after half a year to renew our HeJu energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there we were: One and a half days full of reports, heated discussions, brainstorming and coffee overflow. First of all our spokespersons Nicholas and Sripriya and our four &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/jobs_talents/doctoral_students/helmholtz_juniors/working_groups_activities/" title="Working Groups"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;working groups&lt;/a&gt; presented the progress so far. The main achievements have been the active participation in an update of the Helmholtz Association’s official PhD guidelines (which virtually has some effect on all Helmholtz PhD students), the finishing of our “Helmholtz PhD booklet” (we will keep you posted about this!) and the launch of this year’s &lt;a class="link" href="http://heju-survey.de" title="HeJu Survey"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;PhD survey&lt;/a&gt; (where every PhD student under Helmholtz can actually help to improve the conditions, hopefully you all took part. But, don’t worry if not, it’s still possible until Sep 19th!!! Go for it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_bc838b8887356475.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/events-300x199_hu_a10fb63526318854.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Our events group organized the mid-term meeting and currently develops concepts for future PhD events. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our “events” group who was busy organizing this meeting we’ve been in close contact with officials of the Helmholtz Association and the direct feedback was helping a lot to shape common goals and to identify certain (im)possibilities. For instance, what financial support can we expect and what are the advantages and disadvantages of becoming an official body of the Helmholtz Association? A topic so fundamental, that the formation of a new working group was required to evaluate its pros and cons. But, a special treat for us was the visit of Prof. Dr. Jürgen Mlynek, &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.helmholtz.de/en/about_us/president/" title="HA president"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;president&lt;/a&gt; of the Helmholtz Association, who took some time to welcome us personally in the headquarter and also stayed for a quick Q&amp;amp;A session (see header). How much closer can you get as a PhD student to the very head of your research organization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199.jpg"
width="300"
height="199"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_abed3c62ea1a0cea.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/EmbodimentGroup-300x199_hu_b731d6a0c9399ad.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="The newly established embodiment group will evaluate how to position the HeJu’s within the Helmholtz Association in the future. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="361px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During several sessions the individual working groups discussed and developed new ideas and eventually set the goals for the rest of the term. Furthermore, we were lucky to talk with the public relations officials, who gave us vital support on our visibility and communication structure as well as an insight into their day-to-day work. A result of which we have this brand new Blog you happened to be reading right now and the new &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/helmholtz.juniors?fref=ts" title="HeJu FB"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;HeJu’s logo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is left to do for this year? Of course, the discussion on the PhD guidelines is not over yet and will go on. One goal, for example, is to increase contract positions for PhDs in relation to scholarships. The “survey” group will have a busy time analyzing the survey results and wrapping that up until January next year, when the HeJu’s meet again at the &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.awi.de/en/home/" title="AWI"
target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Alfred Wegener Institute&lt;/a&gt; in Bremerhaven. The PhD booklet will be published and available for everyone who’s interested (some interviews with the people involved will be up as well). We are also planning a special event where PhD students can connect and get information on career options and this Blog will be filled with more articles about our work as HeJu’s and topics about PhD life in general. Feel free to comment and ask questions below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715.jpg"
width="1000"
height="715"
srcset="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_ba63b2c24e57ba16.jpg 480w, https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2014/09/helmholtz-juniors-mid-term-meeting-2014/images/berlinnightlife-1000x715_hu_62e4c2da3df96f65.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="As you might already have figured out, all that talking and discussing made our heads dizzy. We tried to counteract that feeling over a few drinks at Berlin’s open air summer nightlife locations. During which we discussed if the competition for Germany’s sexiest scientist award would be an appropriate HeJu-event to organize. © Sripriya Murthy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="139"
data-flex-basis="335px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>