<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Helmholtzjuniors on Helmholtz Juniors</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/helmholtzjuniors/</link><description>Recent content in Helmholtzjuniors on Helmholtz Juniors</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/tags/helmholtzjuniors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>1st NextGen meeting is coming soon</title><link>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/09/1st-nextgen-meeting-is-coming-soon/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/09/1st-nextgen-meeting-is-coming-soon/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://blog.helmholtz-juniors.de/p/2016/09/1st-nextgen-meeting-is-coming-soon/images/Logo_NextGen_4c_kl.png" alt="Featured image of post 1st NextGen meeting is coming soon" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;28th of September is approaching fast and it is going to be the first PhD retreat of all the Helmholtz institutes, organised by the Helmholtz Juniors (&lt;a class="link" href="https://indico.scc.kit.edu/indico/event/229/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to web page). Three days in Braunschweig for a multidisciplinary meeting that will involve 127 Doctoral Researchers and guests. Prof. Wiesler, President of the Helmholtz association, who believes on the importance of promoting the connection between Helmholtz institutes, will join for the expert panel talks, targeting the “Publish or Perish” philosophy in academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3 days will give the researcher the possibility to network and learn about other institutes and peers research, present their work, as well as meet with Alumni to discuss future opportunities after the PhD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the slogan says, this is a conference organised by PhDs for PhDs and it has as main focus bringing together experts in different disciplines to foster ideas and discussions outside their field. The world is moving to a multidisciplinary approach everyday more, and the Helmholtz institutes offer a variety of expertise that could collaborate together. In this direction goes the challenge of the multidisciplinary workshop that will see different teams compete to plan the best way to colonize Mars - future is never too far! Additionally, science slam will offer an opportunity to practice communication skills, also in an unconventional way - dancing, acting, talking, everything is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as Helmholtz Juniors, are excited for this great opportunity and grateful for the immense work the event group put to make these 3 days unforgettable for all the participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you will like it and it will become the event the doctoral research will look forward in all the Helmholtz centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you there!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>